<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eirēnikon, or, A treatise of peace between the two visible divided parties ... by Irenæus Philadelphus Philanthropus ...</title>
            <author>Philanthropus, Irenaus Philadelphus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12682241</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12682241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65679</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65679)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 354:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eirēnikon, or, A treatise of peace between the two visible divided parties ... by Irenæus Philadelphus Philanthropus ...</title>
                  <author>Philanthropus, Irenaus Philadelphus.</author>
                  <author>Gell, Robert, 1595-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 3-102, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.J. for Nath. Brooks ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Gell by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) 1. What peace is here intended -- 2. Who the parties are that differ -- 3. Wherein the difference consists -- 4. How they fell out -- 5. Wherein they ought to agree -- 6. How they may be perswaded unto peace -- 7. By what means reconciliation may be made between them.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reconciliation --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Peace --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65679:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65679:1"/>
            <p>ΕΙΡΗΝΙΚΟΝ: OR, A TREATISE OF PEACE BETWEEN The two viſible divided PARTIES.</p>
            <p>Wherein is enquired,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What Peace is here intended.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Who the Parties are that differ.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Wherein the Difference conſiſts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>How they fell out.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Wherein they ought to agree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>How they may be perſwaded unto peace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>By what means Reconciliation may be made between them.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel of Peace, and bring glad tidings of good things,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers; for they ſhall be called the <hi>Sons</hi> of God,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.9.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And,</hi> Behold what maner of love the Father hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi>
                  <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Irenaeus Philadelphus Philanthropus,</hi> Presbyter and Profeſſor of the more ancient Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. J.</hi> for <hi>Nath, Brooks</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65679:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65679:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE Godly Learned READER.</head>
            <p>IT is not the duty of a genuine <hi>childe</hi> to be ſtill and ſilent, when he hears his <hi>Parents</hi> chiding; much leſs to be ſo diſobedient as to provoke them with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, O well done <hi>Socrates!</hi> O well ſaid <hi>Xantippe!</hi> When the dumb Son of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> ſaw one ready to kill his Father, the indignity of the fact made him ſpeak, and ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, kill not <hi>Craeſus.</hi> And indeed what <hi>ingenuous ſon</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> can ſee the <hi>Reverend fathers</hi> of it, and the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> whoſe <hi>love</hi> ſhould be as <hi>conjugal,</hi> to maintain not onely a <hi>domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and friendly chiding,</hi> but even open <hi>enmity</hi> and <hi>ſtrife,</hi> ſo that they break out into <hi>ſides, and parties,</hi> and are even at daggers drawing, (as we ſay) what child can ſee this misbeſeeming <hi>contention,</hi> but he muſt <hi>ſtep in</hi> and <hi>part the fray,</hi> he muſt ſpeak a word of <hi>pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>reconciliation</hi> between them? For although <hi>Solon</hi> would not that any ſhould be <hi>Neuters,</hi> when the City is rent <hi>by ſchiſm,</hi> yet he forbids not endeavour of any to <hi>make peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if he or any other ſhould ſo <hi>envy the bleſſing of peace</hi> unto a <hi>divided people,</hi> ſure I am, a wiſer then he,
<pb facs="tcp:65679:3"/>hath ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers; for they ſhall be called the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When therefore I ſaw two parties who ought to be moſt dear one to other, ſtanding at defiance one againſt the other, and no <hi>interceſſor,</hi> no <hi>mediator</hi> of their tribe between them, I was conſtrained to undertake this <hi>Task;</hi> Which indeed is a buſineſs worthy the labour of one far more able then my ſelf. Yet hath no man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed this work upon me; nor had I any other motive, but the love of the <hi>God of peace and love,</hi> who is the <hi>love it ſelf;</hi> the <hi>common love</hi> to <hi>mankinde, the love</hi> to <hi>my countrey</hi> too lately rent and torn by civil wars, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame occaſion, my <hi>love</hi> unto my <hi>dear Mother the Church of God.</hi> So that it is purely a <hi>work and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love,</hi> which accordingly I deſire, may be <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly</hi> accepted.</p>
            <p>I know, it will be queſtioned, who hath made this bold attempt to interpoſe himſelf as an <hi>umpire</hi> between two ſo <hi>potent adverſaries?</hi> I was aware of that, as well knowing, that he who <hi>parts a fray,</hi> oftentimes bears blowes from <hi>both ſides.</hi> And what account do <hi>partial men</hi> make of ſuch? They eſteem them as <hi>neuters</hi> and <hi>luke-warm perſons.</hi> And therefore ſuch have great need to be ſupported and encouraged by the <hi>God of peace and love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> had experience of this when he went about to <hi>make peace</hi> between his brethren, <hi>Exod</hi> 2.13. <hi>who made thee a Prince and a Judge over us?</hi> And what aſperſions ſuffered the <hi>Apoſtles and Ambaſſadors of peace,</hi> and, how contrary to their profeſſion and practiſe? That they were <hi>diſturbers of the common peace, deceivers, enemies to Government,</hi> and many like ſlanders.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65679:3"/>
When St. <hi>Peter</hi> went about to break down the <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-wall</hi> of Jewiſh ceremonies, and ſo to <hi>make peace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he was accuſed of it as a <hi>great crime,</hi> and put to his <hi>apology,</hi> Acts 11. And when St. <hi>Paul</hi> went about to promote the ſame <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> what oppoſition found he both from <hi>Jewes and Gentiles: Scourged, ſtoned, impriſoned, buffeted, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, perſecuted, accounted unworthy to live upon the earth.</hi> Yea, Chriſt himſelf the <hi>peace it ſelf and true peace-maker, what contradiction of ſinners did he ſuffer againſt himſelf,</hi> for the very ſame work in the eminency of it? Wherefore <hi>it is enough for the diſciple that he be as his maſter, and the ſervant as his Lord.</hi> Nor do I fear <hi>to ſpend or to be ſpent for the advancement of ſo great a work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit that mine endeavours might the rather proſper, I have concealed my <hi>name;</hi> as well knowing, that men are wont to make a <hi>God or a devil</hi> of a mans <hi>name.</hi> If ſuch or ſuch a <hi>precious man</hi> ſpeak this or that, it's received as an <hi>oracle from God;</hi> if the ſame thing be ſpoken by <hi>one decryed as ſuppoſed heterodox and erroneous,</hi> it's eſteemed by the ſame men a <hi>damnable errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire therefore, that the <hi>judicious Reader,</hi> will rather have regard to the ſubject and matter before him, then trouble himſelf with enquiring whence it comes.</p>
            <p>But truely there is ſo much the leſs hope of prevailing with men, in this buſineſs, becauſe we ſee how looſely the <hi>bond of perfectneſs</hi> is tied, how weak, how bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> is even among <hi>Profeſſors of Religion,</hi> how loving, how dear, how familiar ſoever they ſeem to be, if a little <hi>honor</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:65679:4"/>or gain accrew to ſome one or other, whereof all were capable, preſently <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>ſtrife</hi> ariſeth, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi> and <hi>evil ſpeaking.</hi> As you have ſeen a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of dogs playing together, (it's a reſemblance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted ſuch <hi>curriſh friendſhip,</hi>) you would think they loved one another extremely; caſt but a bone among them, they are preſently together by the ears.</p>
            <p>And becauſe moſt men are of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> minde, they love to hear <hi>themſelves well ſpoken of,</hi> and of <hi>Sauls</hi> popularity, <hi>they would be honored before the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> therefore they make <hi>a tacite Covenant</hi> among themſelves, <hi>no way to diſquiet or moleſt one another in their ſins;</hi> As if the angry man ſhould agree with the drunkard, upbraid not me with my peeviſhneſs, and I'le not trouble thee with thy ripling. Spare me, ſaith the coveteous man to the <hi>proud,</hi> meddle not with my coveteouſneſs, and I'le take no notice of thy pride. Say nothing of my revengfulneſs, ſaith the vindicative man, and I'le not moleſt thee with thine incontinency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch <hi>Covenants</hi> as theſe ſeldom or never come <hi>above bord,</hi> but are contracted by mutual and <hi>tacite conſent;</hi> becauſe moſt men extremely love themſelves, their eaſe and ſecurity in the fleſh; And while theſe <hi>contracts</hi> laſt, all the devils <hi>goods are in peace,</hi> his wrath, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy, his pride his coveteouſneſs, his uncleaneſs, his revengefulneſs, and all the reſt.</p>
            <p>So that what ever pretence of <hi>religious tyes</hi> there may be among theſe men, theſe are no other then the <hi>bonds of iniquity.</hi> For the true <hi>love</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>urity,</hi> as St. <hi>James</hi> teacheth, chap. 3. And if ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere would not be ſuch <hi>mutual connivence</hi> at one anothers ſins, but a <hi>rebuking of our brother;</hi> otherwiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:65679:4"/>all this pretence of <hi>love</hi> is indeed no other then <hi>hatred,</hi> according to the Lords own reaſoning, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>Yea, among thoſe who ſeem to hold the <hi>bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectneſ,</hi> more inviolably, how remiſsly and negligently is <hi>peace</hi> maintained? A croſs word, a little diſreſpect, ſome ſmall detriment and loſs it ravels all that <hi>love and peace,</hi> which had long time been knitting together: But an <hi>Opinion</hi> that like <hi>Samſons</hi> foxes, <hi>it ſets all on fire,</hi> and <hi>ſcatters them like Babel.</hi> And a little <hi>breach</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es a <hi>perpetual rupture,</hi> and diviſion; <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>that the beginning of ſtrife is as the letting forth of waters,</hi> Pro. 17.14. but he ſaith not what the <hi>end</hi> will be. Whereas indeed the people of God who are <hi>firmely bound</hi> in the <hi>bond of perfectneſs,</hi> are like the more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til and purer creatures, like the more ſpiritual natures; as when the Sun-beames are divided, they immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unite themſelves together again; ſo doth the air and water, ſaith the wiſe man: much more do the ſaints of God, who are of a ſpiritual and heavenly nature; if there fall out any unhappy <hi>diviſion</hi> among them, they unite themſelves preſently together again in the <hi>perfect bond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this people of God invite all men to partake with them, and to be joyned with them in the ſame <hi>bond,</hi> as St. <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in the name of them all, ſaith, <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you, that you alſo may have fellowſhip with us; And truely our fellowſhip is with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 John 1.3.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the <hi>bewitching of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſuch a jealouſie upon every motion made <hi>that way,</hi> though <hi>the moſt excellent way,</hi> that it is
<pb facs="tcp:65679:5"/>very hardly entertained by any, unleſs they know well the <hi>perſon whence it comes, and that he is of their own ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit, in other matters men are not ſo partial and curious; As were you in danger of <hi>wrack at ſea,</hi> or <hi>your houſe were on fire</hi> (which God forbid) and ſome one came out of good will to help you, would you refuſe his help, unleſs you knew <hi>of what Religion he were?</hi> Or ſuppoſe ſome perſon of great quality were dangerouſly <hi>ſick,</hi> and the Colledge of Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were adviſed withal, would a <hi>ſoveraign remedy</hi> be rejected, becauſe offered by the hand of a <hi>plain ſimple man,</hi> unleſs you knew <hi>of whoſe Church he were,</hi> and <hi>what his judgement was concerning predeſtination, election and reprobation?</hi> Certainly that very tender of love in your diſtreſs might prove him a <hi>good man,</hi> at leaſt to you, what ever his <hi>Religion</hi> were: 'tis poſſible a man may be a very <hi>good Chriſtian,</hi> yet of none of the viſible Religions in the world. Nor are you wont to neglect a <hi>good commodity at a ſmall price,</hi> though profered by a <hi>Jew</hi> or a <hi>Mahumetan.</hi> Now, are there not many at this day who <hi>concerning faith have ſuffered ſhipwrack,</hi> making a <hi>naked belief all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</hi> whence it comes to paſs, that <hi>iniquity burns like a fire,</hi> Iſaiah 9. Yea, do not many inſtead of the <hi>fear and love of God, and keeping his commandments, continue doting</hi> (or rather <hi>ſick</hi> or <hi>mad,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>about queſtions and contentions about words, whereof cometh envy, ſtrife, railings, [or blaſphemies] evil ſurmiſes, [or ſuſpicions] perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gain is godlineſs?</hi> And although the precious truths of
<pb facs="tcp:65679:5"/>God be manifeſtly revealed unto them, yet do they utterly refuſe to be holpen, except by ſome of their own party. I thought it therefore moſt ſafe for my ſelf, and more conducing unto theſe mens informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to appear to them under a diſguiſe, that I might <hi>deceive them into a better minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince His Majeſty in His <hi>moſt moderate Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> hath now condeſcended ſo low as may conſiſt with His <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and uſed all real inducements unto <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> what farther means is left for the reſtoring of this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdom, disjoynted,</hi> yea, <hi>broken and ſcattered</hi> like the <hi>dry bones</hi> which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. what means is left for the bringing them to <hi>life</hi> again, but the indeavors of wiſe, pious, and moderate men, their <hi>examples, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> and <hi>prayers: By ſuch moderate men the Kingdom ſtands, and the Church alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what means did the Lord command <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to uſe, but <hi>propheſying to the dry bones, and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying to the windes for a breath upon them?</hi> There is ſome hope therefore of <hi>reſtauration</hi> left, ſince the Lord commands <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to <hi>propheſie to the dry bones,</hi> and ſay unto them, <hi>Hear the word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that the wiſe, pious, and moderate men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>ſtrength of God</hi> in them (that's <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) would drop <hi>their word upon theſe dry bones!</hi> O that they would pray to the <hi>father of ſpirits,</hi> that he would vouchſafe them the <hi>ſpirit of life,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> that every <hi>bone</hi> may <hi>know its place,</hi> and <hi>come unto its bone,</hi> that there may be a <hi>mutual yielding</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the due <hi>meaſure of every part,</hi> that ſo all may become <hi>one body,</hi> as the elements cannot become
<pb facs="tcp:65679:6"/>
               <hi>one body,</hi> while their qualities are in their <hi>intenſe,</hi> but in their <hi>remiſs degrees,</hi> and <hi>tempered one by other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Untill this be done, what anguiſh, what dolour and pain diſquiets and torments the <hi>whole body!</hi> But when every one <hi>knowes his place</hi> and moves in it, as he ought, <hi>with delight,</hi> what a change will then follow? What leſs then even <hi>life from the dead?</hi> Then ſhall the <hi>whole Church</hi> riſe up, <hi>tanquam acies ordinata,</hi> as an army with banners,
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.4.6.4.</note> and the great <hi>banner over all ſhall be love.</hi> Then ſhall <hi>judgement, righteouſneſs and peace be ſet up in the earth; judgement ſhall run down like water, and righteouſneſs like a mighty ſtream, and abundance of peace ſo long as the moon endureth.</hi> Then ſhall there be no more <hi>ſtrife who ſhould be the greateſt,</hi> or who ſhould <hi>rule</hi> others, but all ſhall yield unto the Lord <hi>his Kingdome in righteouſneſs, peace and joy in the holy ghoſt.</hi> O that this were come to paſs in every one of our ſouls.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65679:6"/>
            <head>ΕΙΡΗΝΙΚΟΝ: Or, A Treatiſe of PEACE BETWEEN The two viſible divided PARTIES.</head>
            <p>WHen a Scare-fire is once broken forth, and ſpreads it ſelf, waſtes and devours, and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers all the Neighbor-hood, it is not then due time to enquire how it began, or who kindled it; but it concerns every one then to put to his hand and help to quench it: Nor will I now enquire how our <hi>fire of diſſention</hi> was kindled among us, or who was the <hi>Bontefeu</hi> and Author of our <hi>Combuſtions.</hi> For beſide that, ſuch inquiſition would be unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, ſhould we ſtir the Embers wherein the <hi>Coals of burning Zeal</hi> lie glowing, there might be danger <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and blowing up the like flames of contention. Onely thus much we may ſay in general with the Wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> that onely from pride, comes contention. And ſcornful proud men <hi>burn up the City,</hi> but wiſe men turn away wrath (as the LXX turn <hi>Proverbs</hi> 29.8.) <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuting <hi>David,</hi> troubled the Land, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.29. And another <hi>Saul</hi> like him, perſecuted Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. They both figure the <hi>arrogancy of ſelf-ſeeking</hi> men (that's <hi>Saul</hi>) who envy the reign of the true <hi>David,</hi> the love of God and our Neighbor. Every hot-headed fool can blow the coals of Diſſention, but moderate and underſtanding men one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, men of an excellent ſpirit, or (as it is in the Hebrew, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.27.) men <hi>of a cool ſpirit,</hi> can quench that fire.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall endeavor by the help of God, at this time;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65679:7"/>And 'tis high time, when the ſparks of this <hi>fools-fire</hi> flee abroad in the dark among the ignorant people, in Pamphlets and ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Libels, in Tavern and Ale-houſe meetings, in pot-valor, in ſiding and encouraging either other his reſpective party, in deriding and jeering, in detracting and ſlandring, in rayling and inveighing, it concerns thee, and me, and every one who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs obedience to the Goſpel of <hi>Peace,</hi> to put to his helping hand, and to pluck his brother out of the fire.</p>
            <p>That this may be done, and <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation</hi> made between Parties at ſo great a diſtance, we muſt enquire,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What Peace is here intended.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Who the Parties are that differ.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Wherein the Difference between them, conſiſts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>How they fell out.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Wherein they ought to agree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>How they may be perſwaded unto Peace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>By what means Reconciliation may be made.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What Peace is here intended?</hi> Surely not all that is called by that name. That name is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from knitting together in <hi>one:</hi> ſo that <hi>Peace</hi> in general is an Union or Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But there is a baſtard kinde of <hi>Peace,</hi> which may conſiſt with ſin and iniquity, ſuch as ungodly men maintain among themſelves, who mean while are enemies to the true <hi>Peace.</hi> Such is that whereof <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14. where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet deciphers ſuch a condition as we ſhall finde ordinarily in the world; a mutual <hi>humoring</hi> and <hi>pleaſing one another,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing one to other eaſe and quietneſs in the fleſh; A <hi>Peace</hi> endeavored and purſued by all men, and with all men. And for the greater confirmation of that <hi>Peace,</hi> the Prieſts and Prophets of that time had learnt to ſing <hi>Placebo,</hi> (and would God they ſung not to the ſame tune in our time) they complied with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men for the promoting of their own and others temporal advantages, for the obtaining their corrupt intereſts, gaining for themſelves and others eaſe, pleaſure, profit, credit and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world; whereas indeed this is no true <hi>peace,</hi> but a more <hi>fleſhly ſecurity.</hi> For ſo the Prophet deſcribes it, <hi>From the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65679:7"/>leaſt of them, even to the greateſt of them, every one is given to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs; from the Prophet even to the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly: They have healed alſo the hurt of the daughter of my people ſlightly, ſaying,</hi> Peace, peace, <hi>when there is no</hi> peace. Chriſt came not to ſend ſuch a Peace upon the earth: <hi>Nihil boni eſt in unitate, niſi unitas ſit in bone.</hi> There is no good in Unity, unleſs unity be in Goodneſs. The true <hi>Chriſtian peace,</hi> the <hi>peace</hi> we would promote, is joyned with <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 85 14. with <hi>Holineſs,</hi> Hebr. 12.14. with <hi>Truth,</hi> Zach. 8.16. with <hi>Joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 14.17. Such a <hi>Peace</hi> may be deſcribed <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitas Ordinis,</hi> a Tranquillity of Order; or, <hi>Ordinata concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> an Orderly Agreement of men one with other. For where there's no <hi>order,</hi> there's <hi>confuſion,</hi> where there's <hi>confuſion,</hi> there's diſturbance and breach of <hi>peace.</hi> Where there is ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention (which is oppoſite unto <hi>peace</hi>) there is <hi>confuſion and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil work,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 3.16. Therefore <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> are oppoſite one to other, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. <hi>God is not the God of</hi> confuſion, <hi>but of</hi> peace, <hi>as in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace</hi> therefore conſiſting in <hi>Order,</hi> it involves a relation to another, and ſo is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Relative,</hi> and in reference unto another, whether that other be our own conſcience, when the war of our affections and luſts fighting againſt the ſoul, is ended; for ſo the effect of righteouſneſs is <hi>peace, Eſay</hi> 32.17. Or (which differs not <hi>really,</hi> but onely <hi>formally</hi> from the former) whether that other be God himſelf; <hi>for ſo being made righteous by faith, we have</hi> peace <hi>with God,</hi> Rom. 5.1. Or, whether that other, be all other men beſides our ſelves. And this is the <hi>peace</hi> eſpecially which we ſhould all endeavor to follow; which yet ſuppoſeth the two former, <hi>peace</hi> of Conſcience, and <hi>peace</hi> with God, which is the foundation of all true <hi>peace</hi> with men. <hi>For ſo the Saints are filled with this</hi> peace <hi>by believing,</hi> Romans 15.13.</p>
               <p>That we may the better underſtand this our duty, we muſt know, that this <hi>Peace, Union,</hi> and <hi>Agreement,</hi> hath <hi>Love</hi> for the Root of it. Which being two-fold, either <hi>Complacentiae,</hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolentiae,</hi> either that whereby we love and affect another, <hi>quia
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65679:8"/>bonus,</hi> becauſe he is already good, and ſo we love his vertues and lovely qualities; or elſe that love whe ewith we affect an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, <hi>ut ſit bonus,</hi> though he be bad for the preſent, that he may be good, and ſo we love his perſon, not his ill qualities and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. And to theſe two we may adde a third kinde of <hi>Love, Complacentiae &amp; Benevolentiae ſimul,</hi> as when we love one who hath ſome good beginnings of good wrought in him. According to the firſt kinde of <hi>Love,</hi> holy men of God love their like, ſuch as are Saints and holy men. Thus the Saints are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>friends,</hi> 3 <hi>John</hi> v. 14. And their <hi>love</hi> is ſuch a bond of perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſuch a perfect bond, as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. that it knits all the holy ones of God together all the world over. According to the ſecond kinde of love, a good man may love his ill neighbor, and by his <hi>love,</hi> win upon him and make him lovely. According to the third, a good father loves his towardly childe, that he may grow in grace, and the laudable beauty of an holy life, and ſo become in perſon and qualities every way lovely.</p>
               <p>Anſwerable hereunto, <hi>Peace</hi> which proceeds from <hi>Love,</hi> muſt be proportioned and extended unto men: whereof, becauſe ſome are good, holy, gracious and vertuous, and may be truly called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> Others evil, unholy, unrighteous, and untoward, and though <hi>called,</hi> yet indeed falſly called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> becauſe they have not that <hi>life</hi> which ſhould make them truly ſuch. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there are in a middle way between both: with all theſe we muſt maintain an outward <hi>peace,</hi> but differently; thorough and perfect with the firſt ſort; with thoſe we muſt maintain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire <hi>peace,</hi> which proceeds from the firſt kinde of <hi>love,</hi> the <hi>Love of complacency.</hi> With the ſecond we muſt exerciſe entire <hi>peace</hi> alſo, but not ſo thorough, ſo perfect, and intimate as with the firſt, but ſuch onely as they are capable of, becauſe this <hi>peace</hi> proceeds onely from the ſecond kinde of <hi>love,</hi> the <hi>love of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence or bounty.</hi> With the third alſo we muſt maintain <hi>peace,</hi> ſuch as they are capable of, a mixt kinde of <hi>peace,</hi> temper'd with that which they call nor <hi>lis,</hi> but <hi>urgiun,</hi> a friendly and loving ſtrife and contention, that they may be thorough-lovely, and capable of entire and thorough <hi>peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65679:8"/>
As for the firſt kinde of <hi>Peace</hi> with good and Godly men, it may be eaſily preſerved and maintained, becauſe there is the ſame beſt ground of <hi>Love,</hi> and from hence a mutual affection, and reciprocal compliance, and ſweet harmony of ſouls and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits intimately maintained on both ſides, whether the parties ſo agreeing be otherwiſe perſonally known or unknown unto us, near unto us, or further off from us; <hi>Yet</hi> peace peace <hi>to him that is afar off, and to him that is near,</hi> Eſa. 57.19. as in a muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal inſtrument the greater and leſs ſtrings, though far off one from the other, yet have an harmonical <hi>agreement,</hi> and are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant</hi> one with the other, whether in <hi>Diapaſon,</hi> or <hi>Diſdiapaſon,</hi> the diſtance hinders not the <hi>agreement.</hi> And the reaſon is, <hi>Quae conveniunt in uno tertio, inter ſe quoque conveniunt.</hi> They which agree in one <hi>third,</hi> agree alſo among themſelves. Now the God of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> is the God of all the world; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people of God being every where diſperſed in every Nation all the world over, agreeing in God, and working all their works in God, agree alſo among themſelves. And this is that <hi>peace,</hi> which all good men deſire to advance with all men. O that the Lord would enlarge all our hearts to the enterrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo large, ſo general, ſo neceſſary, ſo truly a <hi>Chriſtian Peace!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>2. <hi>Who the Parties are, who are at difference.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe parties at diſterence have ſome things common among themſelves; And it is a ſad thing to name it: They are both by profeſſion <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel of Peace,</hi> whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Office it is to be <hi>Ambaſſadors of Peace:</hi> Theſe are the Parties at difference. The Apoſtle deſcribes them according to their common Function, <hi>That they are Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.1.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, though the parties at difference have one common Name and Office, and are both called <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel of Peace,</hi> and <hi>Stewards of the Divine myſteries,</hi> yet are they diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed one from another in place and dignity. And ſo there are three degrees of <hi>Miniſters, Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65679:9"/>
It is not my buſineſs or principal intention to decide the Queſtions, whether a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> be one and the ſame; or whether a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and a <hi>Deacon</hi> be diſtinct Orders and Degrees; or whether a <hi>Biſhop</hi> be of <hi>Divine Ordination,</hi> or onely <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution.</hi> Theſe and other Queſtions emergent, have been judiciouſly handled by divers Learned men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Field,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker, Hadrian, Saravia,</hi> and others; howbeit I ſhall not wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Controverſies as I meet with them, but ſhew my judgement, and the ground of it.</p>
               <p>Thus much we may generally obſerve, that although every one of theſe Names importeth a proper and diſtinct <hi>Function,</hi> yet is every one of them equivocally taken in Scripture; as the name <hi>Biſhop,</hi> Acts 20.28 <hi>Presbyter,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.1. <hi>Deacon,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. beſides other places. I ſhall ſpeak of them as they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their proper and diſtinct <hi>Function.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt of theſe, the <hi>Biſhops.</hi> The Name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epiſcopatus, Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> is an Office which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>inſpection</hi> and <hi>overſight</hi> of others; An Office of great care and labor, pains and induſtry: <hi>He who deſires it, deſires a good work,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.1.</p>
               <p>This Office of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Inſpection,</hi> proceeds from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency and growth, according to the increaſe of God in the obedient man, as I ſhall ſhew more anon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> Office is the ſame with the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly ſo named as one and the ſame with the <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> Acts 1.20. <hi>Let another take</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>his Biſhoprick.</hi> And <hi>he who deſires</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Biſhoprick,</hi> &amp;c. Nor is there any doubt but the Office under that name is by <hi>Apoſtolical tradition,</hi> being ſo univerſal in all Churches where the Goſpel was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; which therefore muſt be of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> unleſs we ſhould think that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> delivered any thing to the Church without <hi>Divine Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe there may be greater degrees of proficiency and growth, according to the <hi>increaſe of God;</hi> As alſo becauſe there may be need even to the <hi>Overſeers</hi> themſelves, of one or more who may <hi>overſee</hi> them; <hi>qui cuſtodiat ipſos Cuſtodes</hi> —;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65679:9"/>as <hi>David</hi> though a Prophet, yet had he his <hi>Seer;</hi> beſides the <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves, there have been <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>Such degrees of Proficiency and Orders there were, or at leaſt the ground of them, among the Apoſtles themſelves. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>he was not behinde the very chiefeſt Apoſtles,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. ſuch therefore there were; And theſe were Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to ſupport the Church, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. And of how great extent St. <hi>Peters Dioceſe</hi> was, I know not, but St. <hi>Pauls</hi> was as <hi>Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munical</hi> and univerſal, as large as the Church it ſelf. For ſo he tells us, <hi>That the care of all the Churches came upon him daily,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.28. Nor is the like teſtimony to confirm St. <hi>Peters</hi> univerſal <hi>Archiepiſcopacy,</hi> as this is. And therefore if St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> were an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> and <hi>Primate of the Church,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> was an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> and <hi>Primate of all the Churches;</hi> and the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that <hi>Function</hi> proves him to be an <hi>Archbiſhop;</hi> for ſince <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> muſt be <hi>Biſhops</hi> who ordained <hi>Elders,</hi> ſurely St. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> who ordained <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Next to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in <hi>order</hi> and <hi>degree,</hi> though according to the time of <hi>inſtitution</hi> and <hi>ordination,</hi> the <hi>Deacons</hi> were made before them, as appears <hi>Acts</hi> 6. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Presbyter</hi> is ſo called from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies old, or an old man; yea, honorable in regard of <hi>old age,</hi> which is or ought to be grave, and venerable, and experienced in many things, whence perſons ſo qualified are honorable, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.8.</p>
               <p>Hence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Presbyter</hi> hath his name, which may be Engliſhed <hi>Elder.</hi> We may deſcribe ſuch an one according to his Office, a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Church, who teacheth the Word of God, and adminiſtreth the Sacraments, according to <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.19. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. <hi>James</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Presbyter</hi> conſidered according to his proper degree and rank, is inferior to a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> becauſe a Biſhop is <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Overſeer</hi> of the Presbyters. For although every <hi>Biſhop</hi> be a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> yet every <hi>Presbyter</hi> is not a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Thus every <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> is a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as hath been before ſhewn, but every <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65679:10"/>is not a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which he obſerved not, who therefore proves that <hi>Timothy</hi> was no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls him a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>There is yet a third <hi>Miniſtry</hi> which hath properly that name, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Deaconſhip,</hi> and indeed there is little left of this <hi>Office,</hi> but a <hi>name.</hi> Their <hi>Office</hi> we learn out of the expreſs Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. where we read of the firſt <hi>inſtitution</hi> of it, and the reaſon of it, that they might take off part of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles burden, the <hi>daily miniſtring unto the poor,</hi> that the Apoſtles might be wholly vacant, &amp; attend the <hi>miniſtery</hi> of the word and prayer. Yet were not the <hi>Deacons</hi> ſo wholly imployed in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving tables, but that alſo they preached the Word, as appears in the examples of <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 6. and <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8. who were two of thoſe ſeven firſt choſen to that <hi>Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whereas ſome will not allow them any other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then <hi>miniſtring to the poor,</hi> the after practiſe of the Church beſt interprets their <hi>Office.</hi> And whoſe Authority can we ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner follow, than St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and Martyr, one who immediately ſucceeded the <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> He on the way to his Martyrdom wrote unto <hi>Here</hi> his <hi>Deacon,</hi> to take care of the poor, widows, and fatherleſs; alſo that he ſhould know the Laws himſelf, and explain them unto others. He mentions alſo in the ſame Epiſtle, a third part of the <hi>Deacons</hi> Office, That he ſhould do nothing without the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> For they, ſaith he, are the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and thou art the <hi>Miniſter</hi> unto the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> St. <hi>Stephen</hi> miniſtred to <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>Elders,</hi> &amp;c. So that the care of the whole Church belongs to the Biſhops and Prieſts. To whoſe help the <hi>Deacons</hi> were given by Divine Ordination; and we finde their patern in the Jewiſh Church; as we often read of the <hi>Nethinims</hi> given as <hi>Anxiliaries</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence it appears, that the <hi>Deacons Office</hi> was ſacred, and thought worthy to be adminiſtred by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves; and when they would impart it unto others, ſee what manner of men they require, <hi>men of honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt and wiſdom,</hi> Acts 6.3.</p>
               <p>By all which a great defect is diſcovered among us, eſpecially
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65679:10"/>in theſe laſt times. We have known how to make numberleſs numbers of <hi>poor, widows,</hi> and <hi>orphans;</hi> but how to make choice of <hi>widows indeed,</hi> ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribes 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. if ſuch be to be found, I fear we know not, or regard not. And that high <hi>Office</hi> heretofore <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> is now become Laical, and adminiſtred by perſons of very mean qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; yea, in divers places they are intruſted with taking care of the <hi>poor,</hi> who are very poor men themſelves, and need o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to take care of them. It is an Office now become ſo poor, ſo contemptible, that no Epiſcopal man, nor Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian will ſtrive for it.</p>
               <p>I have deſcribed as briefly as I could, theſe three <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> which anſwer to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern prefigured in the <hi>Church of the Jews;</hi> wherein we finde three like <hi>Orders of Eccleſiaſtical perſons, High Prieſts, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> which typified in the <hi>Chriſtian Church, Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that theſe degrees may not be ſleighted, or thought ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary, or of mans device and invention, the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> had their <hi>Idea</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> in heaven, which <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to copy out; <hi>See thou do all things,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>according to the patern which was ſhewn thee in the mount.</hi> And that <hi>patern</hi> the Apoſtle diſcovers when he tells us, that the <hi>Angels are all miniſtring ſpirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly <hi>Dionyſius</hi> obſerves three <hi>Hierarchies</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> and diſpoſes three ſorts of <hi>Angels</hi> in every <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> and in the higheſt, <hi>Seraphim, Cherubim,</hi> and <hi>Thrones.</hi> In the next, <hi>Dominions, Vertues,</hi> and <hi>Powers.</hi> In the third and loweſt, <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, Archangels</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> which diſtribution is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by ſome of the Fathers and School-men, who from hence have taken their three <hi>Hierarchies</hi> of Angels. <hi>Lucifer</hi> was an <hi>Hierarch,</hi> and had his <hi>Regiment</hi> in the place of this world, if he would have kept it, whereof <hi>Jud</hi> v. 6. ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Angels that kept not their</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> or <hi>Principality.</hi> Yea, he hath yet a <hi>Regiment</hi> in the evil world, ruling in the ſons of diſobedience, until he be caſt out by a ſtronger then he, and hence did his envy againſt our firſt Father <hi>Adam</hi> principally ſpring, becauſe he ſaw, man was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65679:11"/>created to be an <hi>Hierarch</hi> in his place and ſtead.</p>
               <p>But this is evidently enough to be proved out of the holy Scriptures, that ſome among the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> are <hi>Superior,</hi> ſome <hi>Inferior.</hi> So much the very names of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels</hi> import, which yet is ſtrengthned by the exerciſe of their <hi>Functions:</hi> See <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. where one <hi>Angel</hi> meets another, and ſends him with a meſſage to the Prophet, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him not onely to <hi>go,</hi> but alſo to make <hi>haſte</hi> and <hi>run.</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> from hence learnedly and judiciouſly collects thus much; <hi>When one Angel ſaith to another, run,</hi> there is no doubt, but they who <hi>ſend,</hi> are the greater, they who are <hi>ſent,</hi> are the leſs.</p>
               <p>Which collection is far more rational then that of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentleman, who, becauſe <hi>all the Angels are miniſtring ſpirits,</hi> from thence concludes, that all the <hi>Angels</hi> are equal. Without doubt the man who ſo reaſoned, was out of his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Should one thus argue, All the creatures are ſerviceable unto man; therefore they are all equal among themſelves, who would not deny that conſequence out of common ſenſe and obſervation? And ſhall we think, that the onely wiſe God, who hath created ſo various and different degrees of creatures in due ſubordination in this <hi>inferior world,</hi> He hath not alſo ordained and conſtituted the ſervices of all <hi>Angels</hi> in a <hi>wonderful order</hi> in the <hi>inferior world?</hi> Is the God of <hi>order</hi> more pleaſed with <hi>order</hi> in the <hi>earth,</hi> then he is with <hi>order</hi> in <hi>heaven?</hi> Or ſhall we rather more truly affirm, that they who have endeavored to drive all <hi>order</hi> out of the Church, and to bring in an Eccleſiaſtical policy like that of the Cyclops on <hi>earth,</hi> the ſame Titans are become <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>fighters againſt God,</hi> and endeavour to rout and <hi>diſorder the hoſt of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtian religion requires not a parity neither among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor among their Governors. They are not equal, for it cannot be that any Common-weal or ſociety of men ſhould long continue, as the Chriſtian church muſt do, if it conſiſts of an Arithmetical equality: But as by the contrary qualities of the elements, and the oppoſite motions of the Sun, Moon and Stars, thoſe Ordinances of heaven, the world is diſpoſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65679:11"/>and temper'd for eternity,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.35 6, 7.</note> ſo of neceſſity muſt the world of men conſiſt of diverſe degrees, ranks and orders; like the ſtrings of an Inſtrument, if they make melody, they muſt be tun'd in due Symmetry and proportion, ſome higher, ſome lower; ſo among men ſome muſt be high, others low; ſome in authority, others under authority; they muſt not be equal, not all in uniſon: He is but a ridiculous Minſtrel, <hi>Chordâ qui ſemper oberrat eâdem,</hi> that's always harping upon one ſtring. What they alledge, <hi>That he who is greateſt among you,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.11.</note> ſhall be your ſervant,</hi> proves a <hi>greater</hi> and a <hi>leſs.</hi> And though you be <hi>brethren,</hi> yet there is a <hi>firſt-born</hi> who rules over his brethren. Yea, this they themſelves admit who moſt diſpute againſt it, when they conſtitute a <hi>Yearly Moderator</hi> over the <hi>Presbyters;</hi> For although their <hi>Annual Officer</hi> hath no warrant from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, yet in that they make a <hi>Preſident</hi> over the <hi>Elders,</hi> they acknowledge <hi>a neceſſity of precedency and order. For were they all equal, all would command, and none would obey; Every man would rule, and no man would be ruled; Every man would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, and be contemned by every man; No reſpect would be had by one to the vertue and merit of another. So that from this jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diſ-harmony and diſcord, there muſt needs follow a diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common-weal; and the greateſt equality would mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der away into the greateſt confuſion and inequality,</hi> as <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in his 6th <hi>de Legibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it appears that there are <hi>different Orders,</hi> and due ſubordination of them in the Church, and among the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>3. <hi>Wherein do the Parties differ?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will not name all the Controverſies between the <hi>Epiſcopael</hi> men and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> leſt while I go about to make up the gap, I make it wider. I ſhall name thoſe wherein principally the Parties differ, and they are either concerning the <hi>Eſſence of Eviſcopacy,</hi> or what is annexed thereunto.</p>
               <p>The Controverſie between the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> men and men of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> perſwaſion concerning the <hi>Eſſence of Epiſcopacy,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65679:12"/>is either whether it be all one with <hi>Presbytery;</hi> or if it appear not ſo to be, whether it be taken away by the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the former, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> affirm, that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> are one and the ſame. And for proof, they bring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Scriptures, as <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. where the ſame who are <hi>Presbyters</hi> are called <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. where the Apoſtle ſalutes the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> where by <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters</hi> muſt be underſtood, otherwiſe this inconvenience would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhould be many Biſhops of one Sea. Theſe Scriptures are brought by <hi>Hierom,</hi> and <hi>Aerius</hi> was of the ſame judgement.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Epiſcopals</hi> anſwer to theſe Scriptures, affirming, That the word <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> is equivocally attributed to the two ſuperior <hi>Orders of Miniſters.</hi> And that an <hi>Argument</hi> founded upon an ambiguous term, cannot be ſolid and firm. And for <hi>Aerius, Epiphanius</hi> hath ſufficiently anſwered his Cavils, and put him among the Hereticks. And, ſince <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the ſame ground defends the ſame erroneous Tenent, if <hi>Aerius</hi> were an <hi>Heretick, Hierom</hi> herein cannot be <hi>Orthodox.</hi> The Stories of both evidently prove, that <hi>Aerius</hi> magnified <hi>Presbytery, becauſe he could not be a</hi> Biſhop, Hierom <hi>becauſe he would not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> foundation be ſo weak, yet almoſt all the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> are built upon it, againſt the practiſe of all the Chriſtian Churches in all Ages, from the Apoſtles times downward. <hi>Zanchy</hi> a Learned man no way engaged in this controverſie, ſaith thus, <hi>Quid certius ex Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriis,</hi> &amp;c. what is more certain out of Hiſtories, out of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and out of all the Fathers Writings, than that thoſe <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> (<hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi>) have been conſtituted and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Church, by the common conſent of the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>But the Oppoſition againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is of greater Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, than it's commonly conceived. For whereas moſt what its referred unto the time of <hi>Aerius,</hi> we finde exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that name ſoon after the Apoſtles times, as appears by that excellent Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65679:12"/>
                  <hi>Cyril</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſent in the Year 1632<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to King <hi>Charl's</hi> of bleſſed memory, bound up with a Copy of the LXX. as an acceptable Preſent by way of thankfulneſs to his then Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty, for enlargement and favor which by his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters he obtained for the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> of the <hi>Grand Signour.</hi> That Epiſtle was publickly read in the Church in divers places, ſaith St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> in <hi>Catal. Script. Eccleſ.</hi> A very rare Monument of Antiquity, which this latter Age owes to that glorious Kings mercy.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Clemens</hi> is mentioned by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> chap. 4.3. Whom <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Tral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſes</hi> calls a <hi>Deacon</hi> to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe diſciple he was, ſaith <hi>Origen;</hi> contemporary to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaith <hi>Epiphanius:</hi> who was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Martyr</hi> after the Apoſtles, ſaith <hi>Ruffinus.</hi> Others alſo of the Greek and Latine Fathers, make honorable mention of him, as <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Irenaeus, Clemens Alexandrinus, Euſebius, Baſil, Athanaſius, Optatus, Milvirtanus, Auguſtine, Eucherius,</hi> and others, cited by that Learned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Maſter <hi>Patrick Yong,</hi> who publiſhed this and another Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens ad Corinthus,</hi> printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> Anno 1633. The firſt Epiſtle is genuine and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, undoubtedly true, as appears by Teſtimonies taken out of it by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Fathers. This by divine providence moſt ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably was brought to light, after it had lien hid ſo many hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red years; and if it had bin thankfully received from the good hand of God, it might have prevented that <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale</hi> which broke out ſeven years after this Epiſtle was publiſhed. In like manner the good God forewarned the whole Nation by a book found, and ript out of the Maw of a Cod-fiſh in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>-market, on Mid-ſummer <hi>Eve</hi> 1626. a few days before the Commencement. It bare Title, <hi>A preparation to the Croſs;</hi> unto which, two other Treatiſes of divine argument were joyned in the ſame volume written by <hi>John Frith,</hi> who ſuffered as a Martyr in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days: this volume was publiſhed by Doctor <hi>Goad,</hi> under the name of <hi>Vox piſcis,</hi> or <hi>The Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh.</hi> So ſeaſonably was the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens</hi> ſet forth, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Argument importing a like ſtate of things to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65679:13"/>time of 1640. and to theſe preſent times.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was factious, as appears by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. Which yet afterwards returned to their former ſobriety, moderation and piety, as <hi>Clemens</hi> teſtifies.</p>
               <p>And among their Commendations, he mindes them that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that ye walked in the Laws of God, being ſubject to your Leaders, and giving due honor to the Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ters</hi> or <hi>Elders among you.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he exhorts them, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Let us reverence thoſe who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver us, let us honor our Elders,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whom does <hi>Clemens</hi> here underſtand by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but the <hi>Biſhops?</hi> After whom he names the <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> as a diſtinct order and degree under the Biſhop. And to make it appear that the degrees of <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Deacon,</hi> anſwer to the like Order in the Jews <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> as hath been ſhewn, page 53. <hi>Clemens</hi> transfers the ſame <hi>degrees Eccleſiaſtical</hi> among the Jews, to the <hi>Chriſtian Eccleſiaſtical Policy.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>To the chief Prieſt is attributed his proper miniſteries. To the Prieſts are ordered their proper place. On the Levites are impoſed their proper ſervices. The Laik is bound by Laical precepts. Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you, brethren, in his own order and ſtation, give thanks to God with a good conſcience in gravity, not tranſgreſsing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinite rule of his miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And page 54. he refers the firſt Ordination of Biſhops to the Apoſtles themſelves, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>The Apoſtles preached the Goſpel to us from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Jeſus Chriſt from God. For Chriſt was ſent from God, and the Apoſtles from Chriſt. Both theſe were done decently, and from his will. For (the Apoſtles) receiving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and being fully aſcertained by the Reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and confirmed by the Word of God, with a certain aſſurance of the Holy Spirit, they went forth preaching
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65679:13"/>that the Kingdom of God ſhould come. Wherefore preaching tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Countries and Cities, they appointed the firſt fruits of them, having tryed them by the Spirit, for the Biſhops and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of them who ſhould believe; nor was this done newly, for it was written many Ages before,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Eſay</hi> 60. <hi>I will appoint their Biſhops in righteouſneſs, and their Deacons in faithfulneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what marvel</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is it, if they to whom this buſineſs was entruſted by Chriſt, ordained the fore mentioned (Biſhops?) ſince alſo bleſſed</hi> Moſes <hi>a faithful ſervant in all Gods houſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things in the holy books which were commanded; whom the other prophets followed with one conſent, giving teſtimony to them which were by him eſtabliſhed for Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then for a terror to the ſeditious perſons, he alledgeth the Lords deciſion and determination touching the <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> againſt the <hi>Rebels, Num.</hi> 16. When page 57. he infers, by like reaſon, a determination of the Queſtion touching <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>And our Apoſtles,</hi> ſaith he <hi>kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that there would be contention about the name of</hi> Epiſcopacy; <hi>And for that cauſe, having received perfect fore-knowledge, they ordained the fore-mentioned (Biſhops) and gave a courſe how afterward, if they died, other approved men ſhould ſucceed and exerciſe their Offices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much more might be added out of that excellent Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens,</hi> very pertinent to our purpoſe, which I commend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the judicious Reader. Upon the whole matter, we may ſay thus much: That ſince the Epiſtle is unqueſtionably ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and true, and of Apoſtolical ſtyle and argument, the Teſtimonies taken from thence ought to be of more weight with us, than meer humane Authority; yea, and meeting with ſober and moderate ſpirits, they may put an end unto this Controverſie, touching the <hi>Eſſence and being of Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the difference of it from <hi>Presbytery,</hi> according to <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Apostolical conſtitution.</hi> But let us further enquire, whether <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be taken away by taking the <hi>National Covenant</hi> Many of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> affirm it; many <hi>Epiſcopal men</hi> deny
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65679:14"/>it. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> alledge the <hi>ſecond Article</hi> of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> wherein the Covenanter vows the <hi>Extirpation of Popery, Prelacy,</hi> that is, <hi>Church-government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. And this ſuppoſed <hi>Miſ government</hi> being removed, he vows in the <hi>firſt Article</hi> (ſomewhat immethodically) to endeavor <hi>Reformation according to the Word of God, and the example of the best Reformed Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> men alledge for themſelves, That whereas two <hi>Articles</hi> of the Covenant are mainly urged, 1. The <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> a fruitful <hi>Tree</hi> which bare even thoſe who would <hi>root</hi> it up. 2. And the <hi>planting of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Presbyters</hi> in the place of it.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Article of the Covenant, as it firſt came out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> after theſe words, <hi>[according to the Word of God]</hi> was added this ſentence, <hi>which we would have understood tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this Covenant,</hi> or words to the ſame effect. It was put in a <hi>parentheſis,</hi> and accordingly was thought fit by ſome after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be left out. But what ever their reaſon might be ſuch a clauſe was neceſſary to the taking of the Covenant. For it is a neceſſary qualification of the object of a <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> that it be <hi>de rebus licitis,</hi> of things lawful: Becauſe a <hi>Vow</hi> differs onely <hi>formally</hi> from a <hi>Promiſſory Oath;</hi> Now <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum non est vinculum iniquitatis,</hi> an Oath is not a bond of iniquity. Since therefore the holy Scripture is the meaſure and rule of <hi>things lawful,</hi> a <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant to extirpate Epiſcopacy,</hi> could not be lawful, ſince it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, expreſly commended in the word of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides, the Covenant was intended againſt <hi>tyraunicum imperium Epiſcoporum,</hi> the tyrannical imperiouſneſs and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering of Biſhops, as Dr. <hi>Arrowſmith</hi> interpreted that part of the Covenant, in his Epiſtle to the Foreign <hi>Reformed Churches.</hi> It aimed not therefore at the <hi>extirpation of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> it ſelf, much leſs was it intended to introduce a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more <hi>tyrannical domination</hi> to be ſet up among the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> as moſt men complain who have felt it, or feared it. The ſlovenly Cynick who trode upon <hi>Plato</hi>'s neat Bed with his dirty feet, ſaying he trode down <hi>Plato</hi>'s pride, he was not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65679:14"/>aware of <hi>Plato</hi>'s true anſwer, That he trode down his pride indeed, <hi>ac ſuperbia majori,</hi> with greater pride. Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the taking of the <hi>Covenant</hi> doth not tend to the <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irpation of Epiſcopacy</hi> it ſelf, which is an <hi>Office lawful,</hi> and according to the Word of God, and the ancient Laws of this R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, but at the removing the <hi>tyranny</hi> exerciſed by ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who have adminiſtred that <hi>Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Epiſcopal men</hi> acquit themſelves of the ſecond Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> As for the firſt, wherein the Covenanter <hi>vows to endeavor Reformation according to the word of God,</hi> and <hi>the example of the best Reformed Churches.</hi> Here are two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of <hi>Reformation:</hi> 1. <hi>The word of God.</hi> And 2. <hi>The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the best Reformed Churches.</hi> 1. It is beſt to ſay nothing of the former, how ſuitable the endeavor of <hi>Reformation</hi> hath been to the rule of Gods Word. As for the <hi>example of the best Reformed Churches,</hi> it was not without an over-ruling hand of Providence, that no certain and definite Church, whether of this divided judgement, or that, is ſpecified or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Covenant; but it is left to the conſideration and conſcience of every one who takes the Covenant, which <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> and which of all the <hi>Churches</hi> is the <hi>best Reformed.</hi> That we may the better underſtand this, we muſt enquire,</p>
               <p n="1">1. What a <hi>Church</hi> is: And 2. what the <hi>Reformation</hi> of a <hi>Church</hi> is, whence it will appear which are the beſt Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, and which of them is the beſt reformed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A <hi>Church</hi> may be deſcribed a <hi>Congregation</hi> of men fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, believing in him and Jeſus Chriſt, loving him, and obeying him.</p>
               <p>When I call it <hi>a Congregation,</hi> it is not onely to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood an union, or gathering of men together in ſome certain place, as an houſe, or town, or city onely, as examples may be found in Scripture of all theſe; But this <hi>gathering</hi> is more generally to be underſtood, as that which is wrought by the ſpirit of God, gathering all the people unto <hi>Shilo, Gen</hi> 49 10. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1. Otherwiſe how unreaſonable were it (which yet hath been practiſed) that men for their worldly ends, living in ſome town or city, ſhould be enforced to the Religion of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65679:15"/>predominant party in it? When it's added, that this <hi>congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> is of men fearing God, believing in him and Jeſus Chriſt, loving and obeying him, this deſcription comprehends all who can be ſaid to be of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>What then is <hi>Reformation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reformation</hi> is the renewing of the mind and heart acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>ſhape, form, and image</hi> of God. For whereas God made every man upright, (the word is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not proper, but appellative) <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. They had ſought out many inventions, it is neceſſary, that they be not <hi>conformed</hi> unto this world, but be <hi>transformed</hi> by the <hi>Renewing of their minde, that they may prove what is that good, that acceptable, and perfect will of God; which,</hi> while they are <hi>conformed unto this world,</hi> they cannot prove.</p>
               <p>Hence it's evident, that <hi>Reformation of the Church,</hi> is not onely according to the judgement or opinion, (which is rather <hi>information</hi> then <hi>reformation</hi>) but mainly and principally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>will, affections, actions, and whole converſation, Eph.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. Both outward and inward, yea, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.11. <hi>In all holy Converſations and Godlineſſes,</hi> as the Greek words fignifie, being plural. For we cannot know what is the true Doctrine, unleſs we firſt have bin obedient unto the will of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. So that their glory is vain, who vaunt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the <hi>beſt reformed Church,</hi> becauſe they ſay, they are <hi>Orthodox,</hi> which is onely <hi>of a right opinion.</hi> For if their <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> be examined according to the <hi>Lydius lapis,</hi> and <hi>Canon of the Scriptures,</hi> they will be found to have leſs whereof to glory, in reſpect of both, than many others whom they account <hi>hetorodox</hi> and <hi>erroneous.</hi> Whence it will ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that fince the beſt <hi>Reformed Church</hi> is to be eſteemed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Doctrine, the <hi>Presbyterian Church</hi> cannot be the <hi>best reformed,</hi> becauſe it teacheth that the perfect life and life of God, is impoſſible. Alſo,</p>
               <p>Hence it appears, that ſince <hi>Reformation</hi> is according to the <hi>life</hi> of God, and Chriſtian converſation and manners worthy of God, the Church called <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> cannot be the <hi>best Reformed Church,</hi> becauſe they profeſs that their <hi>ſanctification</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65679:15"/>and <hi>holineſs</hi> is onely in part, which the Apoſtle ſaith, muſt be perfect, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
               <p>From all this which hath been ſaid, <hi>Epiſcopal men</hi> collect thus much: <hi>That ſince the taking of the Covenant doth not take away</hi> Epiſcopacy, <hi>neither the Reformation according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches, doth eſtabliſh the Presbyterian Government;</hi> it followeth, <hi>that</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, <hi>or the Government by Biſhops may ſtand, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant: And the Presbyterian Government cannot ſtand according to the Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Difference between theſe two Parties, is in regard of thoſe things which are annexed unto Epiſcopacy, and they are either <hi>Titles</hi> or <hi>Forms.</hi> 1. Titles of dignified perſons, as <hi>Biſhops, Arch-biſhops, Primates, Metropolitans, Arch-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> &amp;c. which, ſay ſome, make men proud and inſolent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiſcopales, ut huic respondeant calumniae Presbyterianorum ne vulgi opprobrio ipſos exponant, ipſorum famae conſulunt atque idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emate Latino ipſis aurem ſecretam ita perſonant. Quod nonnulli autumant, Epiſcoporum, Archiepiſcoporum, Primatum, Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanorum, reliquiſque titulis homines honorates inſoleſcere, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitioſe gerere ſe ſe, tyrannos evadere, populum opprimere,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>non graduum iſta titulorumve ſunt, at hominum vitiaqui ſine dubio indigne ad eminentes haſce dignitates evecti, rectius haec ad mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis radicem, apud ſervulos beſtiaſque reliquiſſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Atqui sperandum non est una cum titulorum contemptu, ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiam, ſuperbiam, ambitionem ac tyrannidem contemni: Fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt qui magnificis jam ſeculi nominibus relictis, in clauſtra ſe ſe abdentes, appellari ſe minores, imo minimos omnium volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. At numquid hoc modo temperarunt ſibi ab his animi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis? Abſit! Refert alicubi Rhabanus Maurus Moguntinus Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas Monachos aliquos in caenobio ſuo ampla patrimonia cum hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus mundi renuntiaſſe; at invidiam tamen, ſuperbiam, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, avaritiam, aemulationem ita non abdicaſſe, uti de uno quadrante acerrime ac ſuperbiſſime vitilitigarent. At iſta longo ſunt intervallo diſſita. Verum ita reformata forte religio nostros omnino ſubegit animos Evangelio, uti nullae ſint apud nos ejuſmodi vel avaritiae, vel invidiae, vel ſuperbiae pestes inveniendae. Nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65679:16"/>ex quo Primates, Metropolitani, Archiepiſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, Epiſcopi, Decani, Archidiacont, reliquique titulis ornati Eccleſiae Miniſtri rejecti ſunt exploſique, omnia cum modestia humilitate inſigni, ſummaque cum aequitate ac animi moderatione geſta ſunt. Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recordemur itaque (res enim recentis memoriae ſunt) quaenuper ante paucos annos excluſo titulorum, nominumque magnificorum tumore, ab hominibus novis &amp; nullius nominis apud nos acta ſunt, eaque ſine legibus notis (quae viſae forſitan reformatae parum, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Chriſtianae) praetextu religionis reformatae facta ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Forum civile primum diſqu ramus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ubi Leguleius pro cliente ſuo uti par erat, (rem geſtam exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus loquor) municipales leges, eaſque ſecundum aequum &amp; bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um regulas obſervandas aliquoties inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſet, non nemo ex judicibus Aulae petivendulorum</hi> (<hi>vulgo</hi> Haberdaſhers-Hall) <hi>ita respondit; Nos non uxta leges communes, non ſecundum Cancellariae regulas hic judicamus, at prout e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſcientiae ſuae dictamine cuique vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum est. Veſtram fidem Lectores! Quae futura tandem reformatio, quae etiam in rebus civilibus judicandis, neque lege comnouni, nique aequitate dirigetur! Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erum autem forum five Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorium adeamus, quod voeant Eccleſiaſticum illiuſque pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper ſcrinia rimemur. Id ex primariis omnium judiciorum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſorum hominibus conſtitit, at prae caeteris ex Presbyterianis, qui vocantur, atque Independentibus. Illi vero vocabulo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatores, appellati, qui quaeſtionem in Eccleſiaſticorum beneficio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cand datos exercuerunt. Famoſum potius quam inclytum genus hominum, qui ſtrenue admodum Tortorum officium praeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terunt; adeo ut exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us non nemo dixerit, Diabolum plane ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fuiſſe, qui ſancto Jobo ſcabiem affricuiſſet, exquiſitius multo atque omni equuleo longe trucufentius atrociuſque fulſſe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſi ad Phalaridas illos</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ingenui viri amandarentur examinandi, ſi quis e clero Epiſcopali ad illos accedat cum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocatione patroni ad pingue &amp; opulentum beneficium Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum poſt quam long a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am dilatiore, moraque diuturmore fatigatus, introitum tandem ad Inquiſitores obtinuit, Deus bone! quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſas, quam ridiculas (quis enim alias ab illiteratis zelotis expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaverit?) quaeſtiones andire ſatiſque facere neceſſe habuit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignus,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65679:16"/>inſufficiens, ignarus, ſcandaloſus reputabitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid in cauſa eſt? mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnus eſt: heterodoxus eſt, uno verho; non eſt noſter: Benefic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um tanti per annum valoris Orthodoxum aliquem conoſtris non dedecebit. At ſuper hac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re aliiiſque pluribus Tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus adeundus. Unum autem exemplum addam quo tandem finiam. Quidam haud it a pridem vir doctu, &amp; partium Epiſcopalium venit in hanc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u iam examinandus. Illum inquiſitorum anteſignanus adoritur; Inter alia conſimilis farinae problemiata, propoſuit iſtud; Quo ſenſu Deus author peccati dici poteſt! Cui alter, quo, ait, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu? Certe nullo, niſi non-ſenſu. Hominem praefidum! impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem! perfrictae frontis! Eo ventum audasiae, uti quis Inquiſitori eique primario ica responſet!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icitur homo, &amp; merito ſcilicet; quippe qui Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia deſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus (nempe, non Dei, ſed Inquiſitorum) qualis ille Johan.</hi> 9. <hi>a Phariſeis pro responſatione haud abſimili excommunicatus. Quid ille? Ad Patronum rem defert. Quid Patronus? Dicam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pegit Inquifitori, [Quare impedit vocant.] Quid Inquiſitor, quid ille? Ad Protectorem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>feſtinat, aſylum iniquitatis. Queritur apud ipſum, contemni Commiſſionem examinatorum. Nihil illam deinceps valituram, ſi legi communi ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iciatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hanc adveertite vos expoſtulationens (Anglicanae libertatis rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que publicae Aſſertores) Quanta olim cura cautum eſt nequando Epiſcopi vim legibus inferrent? Eccos Presbyteros eccos Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (ſuperbum nomen!) qui a nulla omnino lege pendent, exemptos volunt a communi lege ſe ſuoſque. Quod utique documento est fore, uti, ſi quando ipſirerum potiantur, abrogaturos communilege ſuamque diſciplinam pro lege, ſecundum conſcientiae ſue dictamon, impoſituros.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod autem ſititulis ac nominibus honorificis homines intume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcant, at an Metropol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>orum, Primatum, Archiepiſcoporum, Epiſcoporum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>an alienereipublicae conſimilibus: Illi ſunt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſani Presbyteri, Archidioceſani,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>qui ſunt ad illum modum? At hi conficti olim a Presbyteris asque in illorum locum ſufficiendi. Hoc ego certiſſime novi ſtatutum a primariis Presbyterianarum partium neu quid ex immutata forma regiminis honorum titulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runave deperderetur. Caeterum ex his quae conmemorata ſunt, haud arduum eſt conſicere, homunciones, etiam ſine titulis honorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65679:17"/>decoramentis, opprimere alies, ambitioſe gerere ſe poſſe, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcere ac ſuperbire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Presbyters except againſt <hi>Titles of honor,</hi> ſo likewiſe againſt <hi>Forms of Godlineſs,</hi> and thoſe of two ſorts, either <hi>Forms of Prayer,</hi> or <hi>forms and modes of ceremonies,</hi> which conſiſt either in <hi>geſture</hi> or <hi>veſture.</hi> As for the <hi>form of Prayer,</hi> let us firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what that is, againſt which their exceptions lie, and then we ſhall endeavour to ſatisfie thoſe exceptions.</p>
               <p>The Liturgy or Common prayer, ſo called, is a <hi>Syſtem</hi> of ſelect Scriptures, Prayers, and Praiſes proportioned accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the neceſſaries, and ſpiritual proficiencies of all Gods people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To thoſe <hi>under the fear of God,</hi> in the entrance of the Liturgy, certain ſentences out of Scripture are premiſed, ſhewing the neceſſity of <hi>Confeſſing</hi> our ſins, and rayſing our hope of pardon, and forgiveneſs of them.</p>
               <p>Then followes a <hi>Form of Confeſſion,</hi> and after it, <hi>Abſolution from ſins,</hi> and the Lords-Prayer in ſpecial for the <hi>Remiſſion of ſins.</hi> And becauſe <hi>confeſſion</hi> is either of <hi>ſins</hi> or of <hi>prayſe,</hi> after the <hi>confeſſion of ſins,</hi> followes the <hi>confeſſion of prayſe.</hi> Which yet cannot rightly be performed, unleſs the Lord enable us ſo to do. And therefore we pray, that the Lord would open our lips, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Accordingly we give glory to the holy and bleſſed Trinity; And we exhort one another to <hi>ſing unto the Lord, and heartily to rejoyce in the ſtrength of our ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 95. In which <hi>Pſalm,</hi> after the declaration of Gods power, <hi>David</hi> prevents an objection ſutable to their <hi>ſtate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fear,</hi> and like unto thoſe in <hi>Kadeſh-barnea [in the mutable, and unſetled holyneſs of the childe-hood:]</hi> The objection may be framed thus, we are not able through the power of God, to ſubdue our ſins, and to perform acceptable ſervice unto God, and therefore we ſhall periſh in our ſins, and never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Heavenly reſt. The Pſalmiſt therefore dehorts us from hardening our hearts, leſt we ſhould be like thoſe farthers of the Hebrewes, whoſe carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which purpoſe the Apoſtle applies that part of the Pſalm to the Hebrewes in the ſame ſpiritual eſtate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. and 4.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65679:17"/>
2. To thoſe <hi>under faith in Chriſt,</hi> Chriſt is propounded in the Pſalms, (as ſome of the Antients have interpreted all the Pſalms of Chriſt; and our Lord points us unto them, as giving teſtimony of himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.) alſo as foreſhewen in types, and figures of the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſtoried of, and propheſied of in others books of the Old Teſtament; In regard of all which, Chriſt is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> Heb. 13. When theſe have ſome way, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, diſcovered Chriſt unto us, we break out into the praiſe of God, ſaying or ſinging, <hi>We praiſe thee, O God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>After that Chriſt is diſcovered in <hi>types, hiſtories,</hi> and <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> more obſcurely, He is more clearly manifeſted in the fleſh, and expreſſed in one or other of the Evangliſts or Acts of the Apoſtles. After which, the Church acknowledges, and bleſſeth the Lord for exhibiting His Son, according to the promiſes, and his fore-runner <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> Or which concerns all Nations, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 100. <hi>Oberoyful in the Lord all ye lands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then followes the confeſſion of Faith in the Father, Son and Spirit. <hi>Out of this faith,</hi> the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>People</hi> pray mutually one for other. Which done, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> prayes for thoſe things which the Epiſtle or Goſpel holds forth, in the <hi>Collect</hi> gathered out of them; then prayes for <hi>Peace,</hi> and thirdly for <hi>Grace, That we may fall into no ſin, nor run into any kind of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but that all our doings may be ordered by his Governance, to do always that which is righteous in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe prayers, the Petitions are more general, therefore the <hi>Litany</hi> is added, containing more particular Petitions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral temporal or ſpiritual wants of Gods people. Wherein and afterward prayers are made for the King, the Royal iſſue, and ſpiritual Governors, according to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To thoſe <hi>under the love of God and their neighbour,</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded a prayer out of largeneſs of heart unto God, <hi>Unto whom all hearts are open, all deſires known, unto whom no ſecrets are h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, that he will cleanſe the thoughts of our hearts, by the inſpiration of his holy ſpirit, that we may perfectly love him, and worthily
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65679:18"/>magnifie His holy name through Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This cannot be done unleſs the Lord be pleaſed to write his laws in our heart, which we pray for; which done, we return to our prayer, in ſpecial for the King and the royal iſſue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſuch Scriptures are propounded for Epiſtles and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels as befit that eminent eſtate.</p>
               <p>And becauſe they who are in ſuch a condition, have a more explicit knowledge of God the Father, Son and Spirit, and other Articles of the Faith, the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed is added.</p>
               <p>And becauſe prayer is to be accompanied with alms-giving, certain ſentences are then propounded ſtirring us up thereunto. And ſo that Service concludes with a prayer for the whole ſtate of Chriſts Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like reaſon there is of Evening-prayer.</p>
               <p>The explication of theſe and other particular ſervices would require a juſt Tractate.</p>
               <p>Againſt this <hi>form of prayer</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> except: For why ſhould any <hi>form of prayer</hi> be impoſed upon the people of God? Or if any, why ſo long? Why that which is clogg'd with ſo many repetitions? Why not a prayer more ſpiritual? Muſt one and the ſame fit all ages of the Church? Why are Godly men thereby hindred from the exerciſe of their gifts? Why muſt they uſe ſuch a form of prayer, as is taken out of the Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book? Yea, why are many Canonical Scriptures left out of the Kalendar, and Apocryphal placed in the room?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> men alleadge for themſelves, that there is no Church in the world, no not that which the <hi>Presbyters</hi> account the <hi>beſt reformed,</hi> but it hath a <hi>form of prayer;</hi> Becauſe not onely they who are grown up in religion, but the young ones alſo, who are not able to pray of themſelves, may thereby be inſtructed and taught how to pray; ſuch were <hi>Johns</hi> diſciples, and ſuch were Chriſts, whom therefore they both taught to pray. But if exception be againſt a <hi>form, becauſe a form,</hi> every conceived prayer is a <hi>form</hi> unto thoſe who hear it; which is well to be conſidered by them, who except againſt <hi>a form of prayer, becauſe a form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if a <hi>form of prayer</hi> be needful, they ask, why ſo long a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65679:18"/>
                  <hi>form of prayer?</hi> Why hath it ſo many <hi>repetitions?</hi> It's true the <hi>Liturgy</hi> hath <hi>repetitions</hi> in it. Yet are not all repetitions vain or Heatheniſh, ſuch as our Lord forbiddeth, nor for that end; but to expreſs the <hi>fervency</hi> and <hi>ardour of affection.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we read many iterations of the ſame petition or thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving (which will amount to the ſame exception) uſed by <hi>David,</hi> as elſe where; ſo eſpecially Pſalm 136. <hi>For his mercy endures for ever,</hi> twenty ſix times uſed in that one <hi>pſalm.</hi> Yea, and our Lord himſelf is ſaid in his prayer, to have uſed the ſame words. But although this blame were juſtly laid upon the Common-prayer, yet do not many of them who except againſt it, much mend the matter in their conceived prayers; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they uſe moſt what many <hi>repetitions,</hi> eſpecially when they are at a loſs, and know not what elſe to ſay; which is not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And as for <hi>length of prayer.</hi> The whole <hi>Liturgy, Litany, and all,</hi> is not ſo long as many of their conceived prayers. And if their prayers be ſo long, ſurely it is their own fault, if all that time they do not exerciſe their gifts. What they ſay of ſpiritual prayers, are there any more ſpiritual in all the Latine or Greek Liturgies? How much leſs in theſe mens conceived prayers? And if there b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome of all Diſpenſations in all Ages of the Church, why may not this form of prayer compoſed as I have ſhewn, fit all Ages of the Church? Nor do <hi>Epiſcopal men</hi> deny but that many of the <hi>Church-prayers</hi> are extant in the <hi>Maſs-book.</hi> And is it not for the credit of the <hi>Roman Miſſal,</hi> that ſo excellent prayers are found in it? What though all the Epiſtles and Goſpels, or the moſt of them may be read in that Book? Are they therefore one jote the worſe? Or is the Scripture any whit the leſs true, becauſe it hath been cited by the father of lies? Feign the <hi>Maſs</hi> as abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable as any man can make it, will any reaſonable man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe what is unqueſtionably good, becauſe it hath been ill uſed? May not the Sun ſhine upon a dunghil, and yet looſe nothing of its purity? It is true, that ſome <hi>Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> are omitted in the Kalendar, and <hi>Apocryphal</hi> ſet in their place, as the two Books of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> the Book of <hi>Canticles,</hi> the latter part of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> propheſie, much of the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:65679:19"/>and ſome others. And why not? For although <hi>all Scriptures were written for our edifying,</hi> yet all Scriptures do not edifie alike. As for thoſe <hi>Canonical</hi> omitted, the <hi>Epiſcopal man</hi> dares appeal to the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> whether <hi>Adam, Seth, Enoſh,</hi> and the reſt of the Genealogy, edifie ſo much as the Scripture <hi>Canonical</hi> or <hi>Apocryphal</hi> appointed to be read in place of it. Yea, whether the Hiſtory of <hi>Judith</hi> may not edifie as well as the Hiſtory of <hi>Jael.</hi> Yea, why he, though with much ſtudy he hath hardly attained to the true meaning of the latter chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Canticles,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> yet ſhould deſire that the ſame Scriptures ſhould be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the underſtanding of the rude multitude <hi>ex tempore,</hi> and hope that thereby they ſhould be edified.</p>
               <p>The Learned Jews were not thought to envy the people the Holy Scriptures, when they forbade the novices the reading of the three firſt chapters of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and ſome other Scriptures, leſt they ſhould frame ill interpretations of them.</p>
               <p>Many other exceptions are taken by the Presbyterians and others, againſt the Book of Common-prayer; which are ſo frivolous, that its apparent their <hi>Palmarium,</hi> their main <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> againſt it, is, — <hi>Stat pro ratione voluntas,</hi> They <hi>would</hi> not have it.</p>
               <p>But the Presbyterians take great exceptions againſt the Forms of Godlineſs expreſſed in Ceremonies in Geſture, as Bowing, Standing, Kneeling, enjoyned at the performance of divers parts of the Divine Service, with which the Church of God ſhould not be burthened.</p>
               <p>Concerning ſuch <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Epiſcopal men ſay, That a reaſon may be given of them, according to the different parts of the Service where they are commanded to be uſed. Divers of Epiſcopal <hi>perſwaſion</hi> have written particularly of theſe; and therefore I refer the Reader to them for ſatisfaction. I ſhall onely adde a Rule out of <hi>Ticonius,</hi> cited by St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When any thing in Scripture is preſcribed to be done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the circumſtances when, where, how, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it ſhould be done, which yet cannot be done without ſuch circumſtances, that duty to be done muſt be circumſtantiated out of the word
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65679:19"/>elſwhere mentioned, or according to the ancient cuſtom of the Church.</p>
               <p>As when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Preach the word,</hi> yet adds not <hi>when,</hi> or <hi>where,</hi> or <hi>how,</hi> a due circumſtance of <hi>place</hi> and <hi>maner,</hi> may be taken from the practice of <hi>Ezra, Nehem.</hi> 8.4. or of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6.13. where the word turn'd a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> ſignifies rather a <hi>Pulpit.</hi> So when our Lord ſaith, <hi>Baptize all Nations:</hi> And touching that other Sacrament, <hi>Do this as often as ye do it in remembrance of me.</hi> The <hi>mode</hi> or <hi>way</hi> of adminiſtring and receiving theſe Sacraments, is no where commanded, and therefore its left to be directed by the Fathers of the Church.</p>
               <p>But whereas <hi>Forms of Godlineſs</hi> are either in <hi>geſture</hi> or <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture:</hi> 1. In <hi>veſture,</hi> as the <hi>Surplice.</hi> At this ſome take moſt offence, becauſe it is of <hi>humane invention,</hi> yet is it uſed in Gods Worſhip; and certain parts of the <hi>Miniſters Office</hi> may not be performed without it, as the <hi>adminiſtration of Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. 2. Beſides we ought not to conform our ſelves unto the <hi>Antichriſtian Papiſts</hi> who uſe that <hi>veſtment</hi> with very great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence. A ground of great ſuſpition, that it is a <hi>Babyloniſh garment,</hi> becauſe it is one of thoſe merchandizes wherein <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> traded, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.14. 3. Laſtly, all things ought to be done to <hi>edifying.</hi> But what edifying can there be in <hi>wearing of a Surplice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Epiſcopal man muſt ſatisfie theſe doubts, otherwiſe he muſt leave off his <hi>Surplice.</hi> But that he may keep it on, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thus to the firſt ſcruple, That the <hi>Prieſt</hi> muſt uſe ſome <hi>garment</hi> or other in his <hi>miniſtration;</hi> and ſince no certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinite <hi>veſture</hi> is enjoyned him in the Goſpel, the Governors of the Chriſtian Church have thought meet ſome way to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Jewiſh <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who in their ſervice, according to Gods ordinance, wore a <hi>Linnen Ephod,</hi> ſo that they borrowed not this <hi>garment</hi> from the Papiſts. What they ſupect of the <hi>Babylonian ware,</hi> that by the <hi>fine linnen</hi> was prefigured the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice,</hi> is groundleſs; For the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer either to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which may be doubted whether they ſignifie linnen or lilk, as our Tranſlators render the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter word in the margent, <hi>Exodus</hi> 25.4. And if ſo, the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65679:20"/>(ſay they) make us finer than we are; we wear no ſilk Surplices.</p>
               <p>But what if one ſhould queſtion the Presbyterians <hi>Geneva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gown,</hi> as the Presbyters queſtion the Epiſcopals ſuppoſed <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Surplice?</hi> This is not without precedent. A man learned and eminent in his way, one of the late <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> being a Non-conformiſt, he refuſed to wear a <hi>Surplice.</hi> He had a ſon, a pregnant young man, who not onely ſcrupled the wearing of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> but the Maſter of Arts <hi>Gown</hi> alſo; from which ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity his father much diſſwaded him. To whom his ſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this anſwer, Father, if you ſhall be pleaſed to give me your reaſons, why you forbear the uſe of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> I ſhall tell you mine, why I wear not a <hi>Gown.</hi> Nor was this young man alone of the opinion. A good woman once told me, ſhe had no exception againſt my Doctrine, onely ſhe was ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized at my <hi>Gown,</hi> being a <hi>Relique of Rome.</hi> I told her the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of my Gown was not taken from <hi>Rome,</hi> but that it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the faſhion of the Burgomaſters of <hi>Geneva;</hi> which gave her much ſatisfaction. Wo to the Teachers, and theſe who are taught by them! How have they neglected that talent of Gods grace in them, and are caſt into outward darkneſs, even the darkneſs of outward things.</p>
               <p>To the third ſcruple, which only hath a ſhew of reaſon, they ſay, The <hi>Surplice edifies not,</hi> as all things ought to do in the <hi>worſhip of God.</hi> Surely it doth <hi>edifie,</hi> but becauſe fleſh and blood would alwayes be tampering in the <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> its here to be excluded, when we ſay, that the <hi>white garment</hi> doth edifie <hi>ex naturarei, non exhumana impoſitione:</hi> The <hi>Surplice</hi> edifies out of its own nature, not by invention or impoſition of men. For whereas the <hi>Priest</hi> ought in righteouſneſs and holineſs to exceed at leaſt the common ſort of people, the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> is a <hi>diſtinctive Character</hi> between them; And hath in it the ſignification of <hi>inward righteouſneſs,</hi> which the people in their Reſponſe, pray, That the <hi>Prieſts may be clothed withal,</hi> out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.9. <hi>Let the Prieſts be clothed with righteouſneſs;</hi> For the <hi>fine linnen is the righteouſneſs of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 19.8. which we purcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Lord Jeſus by Faith and Prayer,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65679:20"/>
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.18. whence ariſeth ſpiritual <hi>joy and cheerfulneſs</hi> in the ſervice of God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.8. whereby we become like unto the <hi>holy Angels,</hi> Acts 10.30. and begin to do the will of God in earth, as it is done in heaven. So that the Epiſcopal men rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus: If the <hi>fine linnen</hi> be the <hi>righteouſneſſes of the Saints,</hi> according to <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.8. the <hi>Babylonian ſine linnen</hi> will prove the <hi>falſe</hi> righteouſneſs, whereof the Presbyterians have no ſmall ſhare, when they imagine themſelves clothed with the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> and renounce all <hi>inward inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> which is to be fulfilled in us who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>So that maugre all that hath been objected, Epiſcopal men may wear their Surplices.</p>
               <p>But the Presbyterians will not be ſatisfied; but what they want in <hi>reaſon</hi> againſt the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> whether in <hi>geſture</hi> or <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> they make up in <hi>paſſion,</hi> and call the Ceremonies <hi>Popiſh;</hi> and ſay, that becauſe they are uſed by the Papiſts, therefore it is not ſafe for the Reformed Churches to uſe them. Why? Becauſe the Papiſts are <hi>Idolaters,</hi> they are Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p>Nor will I make <hi>Apology</hi> for them, ſaith the Epiſcopal man, no, nor for our ſelves. When men are charged to be <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> is it in regard of the outward <hi>Idol</hi> onely, or the inward al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo? We read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.3. of <hi>idols in the heart.</hi> Does not the Apoſtle ſay, that <hi>covetouſneſs is idolatry?</hi> And that ſome there are <hi>who make their belly their god?</hi> Yea, what if theſe latter be the worſe <hi>Idolaters?</hi> Surely ſince Gods eyes are upon the heart, an <hi>Idol</hi> there is moſt abominable. Are they Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? Does not the Apoſtle ſay, there are many Antichriſts? 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. and are there none of them in us? As for <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Ceremonies,</hi> or <hi>no Ceremonies at all,</hi> if any Church can be without all <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which I much doubt, (for they who moſt oppoſe all <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> if well looked into, have <hi>their Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi>) But if one Church have multitudes of Ceremonies, and another none at all, whether ſhall we juſtifie of the two?</p>
               <p>Two women fell out, the one called the other <hi>where,</hi> the other called her <hi>ſlut.</hi> They are both naught.</p>
               <p>The <hi>multitude of Ceremonies</hi> or <hi>gay ornaments,</hi> may render
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65679:21"/>the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> ſuſpected to be a <hi>ſtrumpet.</hi> Yet the <hi>want of all Ceremonies,</hi> (as decent diſtinctive garments) as they do not prove the <hi>Proteſtants Church</hi> to be <hi>chaſte</hi> or <hi>honeſt,</hi> ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it render her <hi>comely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely a principal regard ought to be had of <hi>Peace,</hi> even with the Papiſts, and how can that be advanced better, than by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with them in what is <hi>orderly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whereas we are bound as much as lies in us, <hi>to live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with all men,</hi> are the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yea are the <hi>Turks</hi> or In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idels excluded from this <hi>peace?</hi> And whereas its injoyn'd, that as much as lies in us, we ſhould <hi>live peaceably with all men,</hi> ſurely we ought to ſeek peace with them in all ſuch <hi>actions, geſtures, poſtures, ceremonies,</hi> as are not forbidden in the holy Scriptures. And whereas the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> is held by diverſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to be a true <hi>Church,</hi> though much corrupted, as a man though diſeaſed, yea full of ſores and putrefactions, is yet a man; we may, yea we ought according to the Rule named, in all things that are <hi>true,</hi> honeſt juſt, pure, lovely, of good report, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Phil. 4.8, 9. ſeek <hi>peace</hi> with them; and with an holy <hi>Spagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rik</hi> purge out whatever is corrupt among them.</p>
               <p>Alas! both they and we are as a company of men faln into a deep pit, and we quarrel one with other in the dark, like the <hi>Andabata</hi> who fought with their eyes ſhut.</p>
               <p>How much more ſafe is it that we all endeavour to get out of the pit of corruption, and become guides to others of ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
               <p>We have heard ſome principal differences between the parties; But</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>4. <hi>How fell theſe parties out?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are different reports, and it is but reaſonable, that we hear both.</p>
               <p>The Epiſcopal man tells us, that the faction of <hi>Aerius,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving how many Eccleſiaſtical Dignities were wiſely confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and worthily beſtowed on perſons pious and learned, they envied the flouriſhing eſtate of the <hi>Church under Epiſcopal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65679:21"/>Government;</hi> and being ambitious of thoſe honours, whereof they were conſcious to themſelves they were moſt unworthy, and deſpairing that ever they ſhould paſs thorow the <hi>Temple of Vertue, into that of Honour,</hi> they reſolved, <hi>Flectere cum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queant ſuperes, Acherenta movere.</hi> And therefore for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of their <hi>envy</hi> and ambition, by their pretence of <hi>piety,</hi> and <hi>zeal for the truth</hi> (that is, <hi>their own choſen tenents</hi>) and <hi>feigned fear of Popery,</hi> they ſtole into an intereſt much ſtronger then their own, whereby they thought, they might command all the world. Under the fore-mentioned pretences, they engaged the mutable populacy already weary and ſurfeting of a long <hi>peace,</hi> unto their party, by whoſe help what could they not do? Some would change the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> others the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> And all preſumed, that the ſword could effect all this. And therefore the yong men muſt be curſed into the war, and the Pulpits muſt ſound with <hi>Curſe yee Merez,</hi> &amp;c. And they did it <hi>bitterly.</hi> Yea, <hi>Merez</hi> hath been curſed on both ſides; and the yong men terrified out of doors, conſcientiouſly to kill and ſlay, and the moſt have been thought to go forth <hi>in their ſimplicity.</hi> O how many thouſands have been ſlain in this and the neighbour Nations! And many of thoſe who returned with broken Legs and Arms, and elſwhere wounded in their bodies, are dead in Hoſpitals, curſing thoſe who curſed them out. Then <hi>the lean kine came forth, and eat up the fat ones;</hi> men of decayed and deſperate fortunes, repaired their eſtates with the ruines of thoſe who were <hi>peaceable in the land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then was a man made an offender for a word; and a ſnare was laid for him who reproved in the gate, and the juſt was turned aſide for a thing of nought. And have we not known notorious whore-maſters, reeling drunkards, profane ſwearers and curſers, abominable lyars, incarnate, envy, hatred, malice and all uncharitableneſs, have we not known thoſe, and a thouſand ſuch masked under the viſor of the <hi>godly party?</hi> For the cover of all this wickedneſs, was that damnable <hi>art of ſeeming Hypocriſy, Hypocriſy</hi> that might be felt, it was ſo palpable. The Epiſcopal man will draw a vail over all the reſt which might be added.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:65679:22"/>
Let us hear the Presbyter. He layes all the blame upon the Epiſcopal clergy and tells us, that their ambition and tyranny hath ruin'd all; That this begun to work in the time of St. <hi>John,</hi> who notes both in <hi>Dioirephes,</hi> then <hi>Biſhop,</hi> before <hi>Aerius the Presbyter</hi> appeared in the <hi>Church,</hi> that <hi>Diotrephes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 3 <hi>John</hi> 9 10. <hi>Diotrephes</hi> was notable for his <hi>ambition.</hi> He might no doubt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, have had the place of a <hi>Primate.</hi> It's neceſſary in every convention of men that there be one <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>firſt,</hi> and others after him. But <hi>Diotrephes</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he loved priority and <hi>primacy.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> blames his ill <hi>affection.</hi> At all feaſts and all meetings of men, there are places of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority; nor doth our Lord diſallow it, where he ſaith, leſt a more honorable man come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Saviour blames <hi>ambition</hi> in them, who <hi>love the upper moſt rooms at feaſts,</hi> and the <hi>chief ſeates in the Synagogues.</hi> Nor doth he diſapprove ſalutations, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.47. but <hi>chap.</hi> 23.7. He reproves the Rabbies affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, <hi>who loved greetings in the markets, and to be called of men Rabbi, Rabbi.</hi> Nor was this <hi>ambition</hi> of <hi>Diotrephes</hi> diſcovered in ſome one act or other, but it was <hi>habitual</hi> in him, the Apoſtle ſaith nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which notes <hi>continuance in that affectation and ambition.</hi> And yet the <hi>Article</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> addes to his <hi>habitual ambition,</hi> he was <hi>notriouſly loving high place and primacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And have there not been ſuch <hi>Diotrephes</hi> among us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, who have <hi>loved</hi> to be <hi>lording it</hi> over their brethren? yea, <hi>above their ſuperiors?</hi> what a ſhameful <hi>ambition</hi> was that, when one <hi>Primate</hi> ſate in the others lap? our Engliſh Story records it. How much greater <hi>ambition</hi> to advance himſelf above the King, <hi>who is ſupream,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter.</hi> (Let his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Succeſſor note that) <hi>Ego, &amp; Rex meus.</hi> I and my King.</p>
               <p>The Kings heart, though he be <hi>ſupream,</hi> muſt not be <hi>lifted up above his brethren;</hi> And ſhould the <hi>Prieſts</hi> heart be lifted up above his brethren? yea above his <hi>Sovera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gn?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Does this proceed from <hi>knowledge? that puffs up,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. or indeed rather from <hi>want of knowledge? A little knowledge puffs up; but a great deal makes men lowly.</hi> A few Peaſe or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65679:22"/>Beans make a great noiſe in an empty bladder blown up; but a full ſack makes none at all. An empty Hogshead ſounds more than a full Butt.</p>
               <p>Or does this ambition ariſe from <hi>power? Surgit animus cum potentia,</hi> The minde commonly exalts it ſelf with power. And then moſt what abuſeth that <hi>power</hi> to oppreſſion and tyranny over others under them. So that it is not ſafe to entruſt ſo much power in one mans hand. It hath been obſerved, that <hi>they who have power in their own hand, unleſs they be awed by the Omnipotent God, are ſeldom juſt,</hi> according to <hi>Mich</hi> 2.1. They practiſe iniquity, <hi>&amp;c. becauſe</hi> it is in the power of their hand; For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>men moſt of all do injury when they have power.</hi> Therefore <hi>Diotrephes</hi> the Primate was a Tyrant, domineered over, and was in urious to the flock of Chriſt. <hi>He caſt the brethren out of the Church,</hi> 3 John v. 10. And what have our Biſhops done leſs? which is quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Saviors precept. It is the ſpeech of our Lord, and the Biſhop of our ſouls to his Apoſtles, <hi>Math.</hi> 20.25. <hi>The Rulers of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and the great ones exerciſe authority over them; but it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Epiſcopal man anſwers the Presbyter, and tells him, That ſome of his party framed a falſe Tranſlation, and he takes advantage of it for his cauſe. For had the Lord given his Apoſtles <hi>power,</hi> it was then lawful, no doubt, to <hi>have power:</hi> And if they had <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> might not they exerciſe it? Otherwiſe to what end had they it, if they might not uſe it? <hi>Quid mihi divitiae,</hi> and ſo why have I power, <hi>ſi non conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur uti?</hi> if I may not uſe it? And if the Rulers of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles might uſe their power, why might not the Rulers of the Church uſe that power alſo which the Lord hath given them? But the words are not well tranſlated; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies word for word, <hi>to lord it, to domineer, to be imperious,</hi> and that other word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to <hi>abuſe authority,</hi> according to the ſignification of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in compoſition. Thus did the Rulers of the Gentiles, and their great ones; but it muſt not be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſts Apoſtles, nor the Biſhops <hi>their Succeſſors,</hi> they muſt not <hi>domineer,</hi> they muſt not <hi>abuſe their power</hi> over Gods
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65679:23"/>heritage, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. the Apoſtle having teſtified his <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and coercive power,</hi> he limits it of himſelf, <hi>Not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that we have dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy; for by faith ye have ſtood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We take notice hence, and let the Presbyters obſerve it, Diotrephes <hi>was a Biſhop in the Apoſtles time, and St.</hi> John <hi>was an Archbiſhop, who threatned</hi> Diotrephes <hi>an Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for his tyrannical abuſe of his authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor do men of Epiſcopal perſwaſion go about wholly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> from all blame. Howbeit, they are not of <hi>Hams</hi> race, that they ſhould diſcover their <hi>fathers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Onely thus much they acknowledge, That great men have great faults; <hi>nor ought we to marvel at the matter,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.8. But among thoſe faults, certainly this was not the leaſt, That, whether through <hi>indulgence</hi> or <hi>conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</hi> or down-right <hi>negligence,</hi> they ſuffered a <hi>foreign govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to grow up under them, even to the <hi>extirpation</hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and with them, of the <hi>Kingly Power which protected them.</hi> A moſt grievous, lamentable, and deplorable ruine!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At neutratamen authoritas peſſundata ſimul poteſt &amp; ſemeluno niſu reſtaurari. Etiam licita, poſt abuſum, poteſtas haud potest fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile redintegrari. Pientiſſimus ac prudentiſſimus Rex regimini ſuo rectam init viam, ſubditos bonis moribus atque homine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano dignis inſtrnit, &amp; monita de regno Dei praeſtruit regno ſuo: atque adeo authomitate Dei in ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is hominum autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it atem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmat ſuam; Et ſic juſtitia ſtabilit ſollum ſuum? An non &amp; hoc firmiſſinaum Eccleſiaſticae Hierarchiae fulumentum. An non hoc &amp; ipſi maxime <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>? An alias unquam populo perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debiturjus eſſe divinum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſcopatus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reverendi Patres Eccleſiae ſiliorum ſuorum querelas audire ne dediguentur. Severius olim juſto atque haud paterne actum, ubi aures amputatae illis qui Epiſcopis obedire detrectarunt: Quamvis eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> illi hac contumelia digniſſimi, at hi cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indigni qui face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent tamen. Fest is etiam diebus, utut precibus communibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuerint, ſuae cuique vocationi, per Apparitores, haud licitum vacare, cum tamen ſox diebus hebdomatim Dominus labor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit. Curias Eccleſiaſticas aliquoties reculis nullius momenti tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65679:23"/>Levibus eas alicubi perſonis, non Dei timentibus admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrari unde Officiales ab officiend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, non ab officie fortiri nomen. In rebus Eccleſiaſticis dijudicandis idoneos eſſe magis Epiſcopo Presbyteros, eoſque pro veteri more, quam laitos, (ut factum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando perperam) Aſſeſſores. Excommunicationum fulmina pro cauſis nihil ſaepius emitti, cum tamen haud vacet exignis rebus adeſſe Jovi; nec de minimis curet lex. Caeremonias cortice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis curari magis quam medullam ejus, pietatem morumque probitatem. Genuflexiones ad menſam ſacram ſine Canore om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino fieri. Nimirum his induci facillime opinionem ſcandaloſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimam ac periculoſiſſimam tranſubſtantiationis; atque adeo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutionem qualis olim temporibus Marianis. Imo &amp; horrendum illud nuperum civile bellum utut etiam aliae cauſae procrearint, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſema tamen ea fuiſſe creditur, quod religioſuli (non dico quam religioſe, quam licite, quam pie) turbas ideo moverint, ne res eo in loco eſſent quo dudum fuerant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Superpellicum &amp; caetera ornamenta Eccleſiae ac caeremonias haud <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ac vehementer urgenda; verum illa ſeuſini rectius ac pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentim inducenda. Siquidem licet illa longa ſint antiquitate ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neranda, novae tamen hominum generation nova plane atque no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter inventa exiſtimantur, ideo quod aliquandiu deſuetudino in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terciderint: iique rebus jam novis ſtudere videntur, qui laudabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les tantum Eccleſiae mores conantur antiques inſtaurare. Caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monias Eccleſiae paſſim exercere, nullam tamen expoſitionem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, nullum Rationale divinorum, quo rerum in Eccleſia it a vel ſecus geſtarum ratio reddatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deſinam jam tandem plurium. Prodiit libellus ante pauoos dies, cui pro titulo est Non-conformiſta, de precibus communibus &amp; caeremoniis in quo, ſi qua vel Topica, vel <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, contra Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugriam Anglicanam, omnia <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> corraduntur. Totus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ille libellus ect recocta crambe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Optabile tamen est uti reverendi Patres illa quae vere ſunt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendicula e medio mature tollant, omnemque ſcrupulum ſi fieri poſſit, examinant ex anin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is dubitantium. Nimirum utut in illo libello haud pauca ſint quae vel ex ignorantia, vel e partium ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio profecta, quae contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ilitant argumenta, tamen haud dubie nonnulla ſunt qua ſolidam responſionem poſtulant. Quale illud est
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65679:24"/>in ſepeliendi formula: Ubi cadaver (forte nebulonis improbi) hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo committitur</hi> firma certaque ſpe reſurrectionis ad vitam aeternam. <hi>Quam nemo quiſquam ſanus concipit. At Presbyter it a dieat, opertet. Hoc atque alia certe quandiu proſtant omnium oculis, nec iiſdem ſatis aperte fiat, omnino vera eſſe ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus &amp; illiteratis atque <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> videbuntur. Unde ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciones ac ſuſurri, odia mutua, &amp; invidiae, animoſitates atque aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationes, &amp; quid mali non inde oborietur?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neque par eſt ut iſta ſola prudentiſſimi pretiſſimique Regis ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantur authoritate, alias plurimum valitura; ſiquidem in rebus ad religionem intime ſpectantibus, ubi cum Deo ummediate agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, neceſſe est uti mandata ſua veritate ratione, inſitoque ſuo pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere convincant animos hominum; Caeteroqui humana ſola autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate mixa &amp; ſuffulta, dempta authoritate illa (quid enina ni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere poſſit pro ſuo Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> arbitrio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſires exigat,) ſua levitate ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; contempta evaneſcent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But while the Epiſcopal man acknowledgeth ſome miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages by ſome perſons under the Government of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> he enquires, Were there none committed by the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> in that very time when they were <hi>Probationers</hi> for their <hi>New Government,</hi> and when Policy might have enclined them to more plauſible and gentle demeanour, whereby they might have won upon the affections of the people? However, was it reaſonable or equal, that the faults of ſome one or few, ſhould redound to the blame, yea <hi>extirpation</hi> of the whole Community? Judge righteous judgement. Is it juſt, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome <hi>Aldermen</hi> have been faulty in the Tranſactions of theſe late times, therefore the <hi>whole rank and order</hi> of them ſhould be taken away? Or, becauſe ſome <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have been zealous and pragmatical in many unwarrantable actions, is it therefore juſt or reaſonable, that the whole order of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> ſhould be <hi>extirpated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O that theſe divided Parties would leave off the blaming one another, and would enquire,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65679:24"/>
               <head>5. <hi>Wherein they ought to agree.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe endeavors of moſt men towards <hi>pacification,</hi> have been ſpent in preſenting certain Tenents and Principles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they would that all men ſhould agree. Hence the <hi>formula concordiae</hi> was framed, and many other <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Articles</hi> of Religion, as thoſe of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But its worth the enquiry, whether all theſe pretences of <hi>Agreement</hi> tend not rather to <hi>diviſion</hi> and <hi>diſagreement</hi> than union amongſt men; that in ſome particular <hi>Opinions</hi> ſome might <hi>accord,</hi> and in others oppoſe all other men. To this purpoſe pains have been lately taken.</p>
               <p>But the iſſue hath been <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>diviſion:</hi> Becauſe they have endeavored ſuch an Union as ſhould be made by <hi>equivocal</hi> and <hi>amphibological Phraſes,</hi> which may be underſtood and taken divers ways, which could hold men no longer together than that Artifice was unridled. And if men agreed in theſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, then they were on this ſide, or that, which gloried by encreaſe of their party.</p>
               <p>Thus the Phariſees compaſſed Sea and Land to make <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes.</hi> And many like them, have labored to make men <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox,</hi> as they ſpeak, that is, to bring men to their opinions, to <hi>think as they think,</hi> while mean time little or no regard hath been had of the Chriſtian life; nor do men conſider, that it matters not much of what Religion or Opinion any man is, if he be a knave.</p>
               <p>The holy Scripture directs us not ſo much to <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Speculation,</hi> as to <hi>good affection, life, and practiſe. If thou do well, &amp;c.</hi> Gen. 4. <hi>Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, &amp;c.</hi> Eſay 1. <hi>He hath ſhewen thee, O man, what is good, &amp;c.</hi> Micah 6. <hi>Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. Bring forth fruits worthy amendment of life,</hi> Math. 3. In every Nation they that fear God and work righteouſneſs are accepted of him. Otherwiſe, to <hi>dogmatize, to know,</hi> and <hi>believe,</hi> and hold this or that <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> without the <hi>life, affection,</hi> and <hi>action, cui bono?</hi> to what what purpoſe is it? See what account the Spirit of God makes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65679:25"/>of ſuch <hi>Theory</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> ſee <hi>Romans</hi> 2. and <hi>James</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>What then is it wherein we ſhould agree?</p>
               <p>That wherein they who differ, and we all ought to <hi>agree,</hi> is the <hi>wiſdom and life of God in righteouſneſs and holineſs of truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>wiſdom</hi> is <hi>begun</hi> in the <hi>fear of God:</hi> The <hi>progreſs</hi> of it, is in <hi>faith and hope:</hi> The <hi>conſummation</hi> of it, is in the <hi>love of God and our neighbor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The life of God is that, from which we have been all alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and unto which we are again lovingly called. The <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetypon</hi> of this is God himſelf, who is our <hi>life;</hi> and the Son of God who is our <hi>life,</hi> and the Spirit of God, which alſo is the Spirit of <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>life</hi> is explicated in <hi>righteouſueſs,</hi> which comprehends all graces and vertues; of which that Poet, whoſe verſes were accounted Oracles, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: which <hi>Tully</hi> turn'd, <hi>Juſtitia in ſe ſe virtutes continet o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes.</hi> And we may Engliſh it, <hi>In righteouſneſs all vertues are contained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>effect of this righteouſneſs is peace;</hi> whence another of the old Poets in his <hi>Genealogy of Vertues and Graces,</hi> which he calls <hi>Gods,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Peace is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Justice and Equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This divine life came forth from the Lord in all purity. This was prefigured by <hi>Eve</hi> taken out of <hi>Adam,</hi> that is the life (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) taken out of Chriſt, of whom then to come, <hi>Adam was a figure,</hi> Rom. 5. This <hi>Eve</hi> is the mother of all thoſe who truly <hi>live,</hi> as <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>the mother of us all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this <hi>life</hi> came ſpotleſs and pure out of Gods hands, ſo it muſt return unto him. And therefore <hi>Christ loved his Church, and gave himſelf for it, that he might ſanctifie it, and cleanſe it with waſhing of water by the Word, that he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh,</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians 5.25, 26, 27. Hitherto we are to be gathered, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1. Hither tend all the labors of the Biſhops and Presbyters. Herein we all ought to meet, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.</p>
               <p>This <hi>divine life</hi> hath been much obſcured and counterfeited by all ſorts of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>falſe Chriſtians,</hi> and is ſaid for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65679:25"/>that reaſon, <hi>to be taken from he earth.</hi> The Lord Jeſus there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeared to make diſcovery of this <hi>divine life,</hi> John 17. <hi>This is life eternal to know thee, and whom thou haſt ſent, Joſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that he hath conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death, and doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>enlighten</hi> or <hi>illuſtrate the life</hi> which was darkened and obſcured before, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. And it is more and more diſcovered in the growth of it.</p>
               <p>For as there are different <hi>ages</hi> in the <hi>natural life,</hi> ſo likewiſe are there in the <hi>ſpiritual life.</hi> And the <hi>wiſdom of God enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy ſouls according to the ages,</hi> Wild. 7.27. To which purpoſe, the Apoſtle is to be underſtood, Epheſ. 4 7. <hi>Unto every one of us is given grace, according to the meaſure <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of the gift Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>of Chriſt himſelf who is that gift,</hi> as our Lord calls Himſelf <hi>the gift of God,</hi> John 4. For as the viſible ſun, by few or many and often revolutions, makes a like number of <hi>natural days</hi> or years in the outward and viſible world; after the ſame proportion, in the inviſible and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual world, the <hi>ſun of Righteouſneſs</hi> lifts up the light of his countenance on the ſouls <hi>of thoſe who fear him, on whom he ariſeth,</hi> Malach. 4.2. And accordingly make ſome <hi>younger,</hi> ſome <hi>elder,</hi> ſome <hi>old aged men.</hi> For if in truth and in Gods computation, they were <hi>elder</hi> or <hi>yonger,</hi> whom the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts ſuch, who ſhould be more <hi>full of days</hi> then <hi>Adam and Methuſala?</hi> Who yet are never, in all the Scripture ſaid to be <hi>old men.</hi> But <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithful, <hi>who had ſoon Chriſts days,</hi> is ſaid to die in a <hi>good old age,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua, Job, David, Jehoida,</hi> with ſome others, all children in reſpect of thoſe two, are yet ſtyled <hi>old men and full of days;</hi> when yet the eldeſt of them all, if we regard their <hi>natural life,</hi> in this outward world, came ſhort of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Methuſala,</hi> many hundred years.</p>
               <p>The Wiſe man ſpeaks home to this, <hi>Wiſdom</hi> 4.8, 9. That <hi>honorable old age is not that which ſtandeth in length of time, nor that is meaſured by number of years, but wiſdom is the gray hair unto men, and the unſpotted life is old age.</hi> And ſpeaking of <hi>Enoch</hi> the yongeſt of all thoſe <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> in regard of natural life, and the father of <hi>Methuſala</hi> the <hi>eldeſt; he being made perfect in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65679:26"/>a ſhort time, fulfilled a long time.</hi> They who are grown up in this divine <hi>wiſdom and life of God,</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>old men</hi> and <hi>Senators.</hi> Thus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> ſuch as are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in that honorable <hi>Function,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. So they were called <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> becauſe they were <hi>ſent</hi> by the Lord, what ever their <hi>natural age</hi> was.</p>
               <p>They who were further growen up in the <hi>divine wiſdom and life of righteouſneſs,</hi> were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> And from the name <hi>Presbyter,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Prieſter, Prieſts</hi> have their name by a contraction.</p>
               <p>Which is an honorable title, and ſuch as was common with <hi>princes;</hi> as the <hi>Prieſt of On, Gen.</hi> 41. may be as well rendred, the <hi>Prince of On.</hi> David's ſons were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Princes,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. They who were the moſt aged and <hi>eldeſt</hi> in this <hi>divine life,</hi> were the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or the <hi>Biſhops</hi> their Succeſſors; whence <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus Lib.</hi> 6. Strom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Proficiencies of the Church of Biſhops, Presbyters, Deacons. So that neither <hi>Biſhops</hi> nor <hi>Presbyters</hi> are of their own, or any other mans making; <hi>not of men, nor by men,</hi> Gal. 1.1. Paul <hi>planteth, and</hi> Apollo <hi>watereth, but the Lord himſelf giveth the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi> For as in natural aggeneration, the man may eat and drink, but the encreaſe is not in his choice, he cannot add one cubit to his ſtature; even ſo a man may partake of ſpiritual nouriſhments, and <hi>feed on faith,</hi> but his <hi>encreaſe</hi> and <hi>proficiency</hi> is not in his one choice, but the Lord gives it. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhews wherein his Presbytery conſiſted, <hi>viz.</hi> in the participation of the death and life of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 5.1. <hi>A w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>neſs of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of the glory that ſhall be revealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And St. <hi>Paul</hi> proves his <hi>Apoſtleſhip</hi> by his ſight of the Lord, and he tells the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that the holy Ghoſt had made them <hi>overſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or Biſhops <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Act.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>But theſe were made immediately of God, we read of thoſe alſo who were made by men. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. However that be true, yet mans conſtitution of <hi>Elders,</hi> preſuppoſeth Gods preceding work in them. Thus the Lord commands <hi>Moſes</hi> to look out
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65679:26"/>ſuch <hi>Elders</hi> as he knew to be ſuch, <hi>Num.</hi> 11. And in our <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the perſons to be <hi>ordained,</hi> are required to give an account what motions and inclination of Gods ſpirit they have had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to that holy <hi>function.</hi> And in this regard the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and other <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church are called <hi>Gods gifts unto men, Eph.</hi> 4. Nor doth our Lord any where ſay, that he will put an end unto, or change that diſpenſation: ſo that we may always expect thoſe <hi>gifts</hi> from God unto his Church, untill the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nction</hi> or ſpirit of God ſo teach ſome men, that they ſhall not need that any man teach them. Such a ſtate there is, whereunto ſome had attained, unto whom St. <hi>John</hi> wrote, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. <hi>The anointing which ye have received of him, abideth in you; And ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you of all things,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whereas therefore ſome at this day diſpute againſt an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate call</hi> from God, they go about to take away Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting work, when he gives his <hi>gifts</hi> unto men; and take the whole work of making <hi>Miniſters</hi> unto themſelves; ſo that ſuch are not <hi>Miniſters</hi> of God, but mans onely; becauſe they have not Gods <hi>immediate call</hi> to the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> nor his preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting work in them.</p>
               <p>I am aware of a doubt, which this aſſertion leaves behind it; For if the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church be of Gods making in ſuch a ſenſe as I have ſhewen, how then doth the King make <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Biſhops,</hi> and other <hi>Miniſters of that Hierarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer: Both may conſiſt. For as the God of <hi>order</hi> hath made man according to his <hi>image,</hi> which eſpecially conſiſts in his <hi>dominion</hi> over the creatures; ſo he hath made <hi>Kings and Potentates</hi> and generally the <hi>higher Powers</hi> in a more peculiar manner after his <hi>image,</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>dominion</hi> over men; whence it is that he hath diſtinguiſhed mankind, into ſuperiors and inferiors, and ſtampt his character and mark of diſtinction upon both. On <hi>Kings, Potentates and the higher Powers,</hi> no hath imprinted <hi>multum Dei,</hi> ſaith Aquinas, <hi>much of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 82. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10 35</note> and ſo makes them like himſelf, <hi>Gods,</hi> as the Scripture calls them; and our Lord acknowledgeth them ſuch, and gives the reaſon, he calls them <hi>Gods, to whom the word,</hi> viz. the <hi>eſſential word</hi> of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65679:27"/>God came, <hi>by whom Kings reign</hi> (ſo <hi>Ireuaeus</hi> underſtood it) to whom the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>image</hi> of God came, and that gives them <hi>now hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10 &amp; 12.6.</note> and <hi>turns them into other men,</hi> and ſo <hi>makes them</hi> as the Lord is ſaid to have <hi>made Moſes and Aaron,</hi> that is, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced them, as our Tranſlators render the word.</p>
               <p>For beſides thoſe perſonal endowments of the <hi>higher powers,</hi> no doubt other <hi>Gratiae gratis data</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are attending on thoſe high <hi>Functions. Wet ye not, ſaith</hi> Joſeph, <hi>that ſuch a man as I can divine?</hi> And <hi>Caiaphas ſpake not that of himſelf, but being the high Brieſt that year, he propheſied,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John.</hi> When a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of men ſtood about that fiery furnace, whereinto the three captives were caſt, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> alone ſaw the fourth who was like the Son of God. <hi>Cur tibi ſoli innotuit?</hi> ſaith Hippolytus, How cameſt thou alone to ſee this? He gives rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>The heart of the King is in the hand of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as the <hi>God of Order</hi> inwardly enables the <hi>higher powers,</hi> by the impreſſion of his <hi>image,</hi> ſo he makes them outwardly to be acknowledged ſuch by imprinting on them that excellency of dignity and honor which we call <hi>Majeſty,</hi> which is originally in God himſelf, from whom it is derived to <hi>Kings and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,</hi> his <hi>images</hi> on earth, as even the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> could ſay. A Character ſo indelible, that even in the wracks and downfalls of Princes, it might yet be diſcerned. For ſo we read, that the Roman <hi>Lictor</hi> an able yong man and armed, being ſent to kill <hi>Marius</hi> the <hi>Conſul,</hi> now proſcribed, decrepit, unarmed, alone, impriſoned, yet he durſt not ſtrike him, being himſelf firſt ſtricken with the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Marius.</hi> And when the news was brought to <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> that <hi>Vitellius</hi> was overthrowen, there ſuddenly appeared in his countenance, a <hi>luſtre of Majeſty</hi> never obſerved before. Such was that which appeared in the face of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Num.</hi> 11. <hi>Judg.</hi> 6 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.26.</note> ſo that the people could not behold him. <hi>The wiſdom of a man maketh his face to ſhine,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> The like may be argued in the ſeventy Elders, in <hi>Gideon,</hi> in <hi>Saul,</hi> in <hi>David,</hi> in <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as the God of Order makes this impreſſion of <hi>Majeſty</hi> in <hi>ſuperiors,</hi> ſo he imprinteth an agnition of it in <hi>inferiors. There went a band of men after</hi> Saul, <hi>whoſe hearts God had
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65679:27"/>touched,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. And <hi>he it is,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, who ſubdues the people under me.</hi> He it is who toucheth the hearts with love or fear, or hope, or ſome other way beſt known to himſelf, and ſo wins them to ſubmiſſion. For indeed who can conceive it other then <hi>divine ordination</hi> that ſo many multitudes of men of ſo various, ſo contrary <hi>natures, tempers, diſpoſitions, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould all ſubmit and yield ſubjection to one or few of the <hi>ſame mold and like affections?</hi> Surely it is no other then the Lords doing, and it is wonderful in our eyes.</p>
               <p>This generally and neceſſarily premiſed, we may add ſome what more particularly concerning the Kings of this Land, That our Common Laws acknowledge them to be certain <hi>Gods</hi> upon earth, and aſcribe unto them a kinde of <hi>ommipreſence,</hi> and <hi>ubiquity, perfection,</hi> and <hi>immortality,</hi> and other excellencies like thoſe of the divine nature.</p>
               <p>And if our <hi>Laws and Lawyers</hi> acknowledge thoſe, and aſcribe them <hi>generally to their Kings,</hi> how much more ſhould the <hi>Divines</hi> own in their <hi>good Kings,</hi> not onely thoſe which the School-men call <hi>gratiae gratis datae,</hi> but much more the <hi>gratiae gratum faciextes,</hi> as the <hi>divine wiſdom</hi> and <hi>piety, goodneſs</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> and <hi>compaſſion,</hi> &amp;c. Such as, without flattery, all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial men own in our preſent <hi>Soveraign,</hi> even in their emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, together with a ſpirit of diſcerning.</p>
               <p>Whereby he is enabled to diſcover the ſeveral <hi>proficiencies and growths</hi> of Gods graces in good men, according to the <hi>encreaſe of God</hi> in them. When therefore he conferres digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on perſons duely qualified, he owns the gifts of God in them. Which becauſe it is difficult, the wiſe man referres the Kings detemination unto an higher principle no other then <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> Prov 16.10. where he ſaith, that <hi>a divination, divine ſentence, or oracle is in the lips of the King; his mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h tranſgreſſeth not in judgement.</hi> And although there are who would reſtrain this to <hi>civil affaires,</hi> and the deciſion of them; yet according to that <hi>preſence of God with Kings, wiſe and good Kings, Solo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oon</hi> may be underſtood to ſpeake of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine matters,</hi> and the diſpoſing, and ordering of them alſo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whereas <hi>Ejuſdem poteſtatis eſt tollere &amp; ponere,</hi> it belongs to the ſame power to put out of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65679:28"/>place, and put in place, to diſhonour and dignifie; the King hath a precedent for both in the wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> who <hi>thruſt out Abiathar from being Prieſt unto the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 2.27. And Verſe 35. <hi>he put Zadok the Prieſt in the room of Abiathar.</hi> And although <hi>Bellarmin</hi> would not have <hi>Solomon</hi> do this <hi>ut Rex</hi> but <hi>ut Propheta,</hi> not as a <hi>King,</hi> but as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> what is that diſtinction worth, if the King be guided with the ſame good ſpirit of God? as hath been ſhewen.</p>
               <p>Would God theſe ungrateful nations did not too much verifie what is propheſied of theſe laſt times, 2 <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>They ſhall not regard their King nor Princes!</hi> O that the character which <hi>Gildas Sapiens</hi> gave of the <hi>Britains</hi> before the Conqueſt, and their unthankfulneſs to their beſt Kings, were not too true of many in this preſent generation! <hi>Si quis Regum mitior &amp; veritati aliquatenus proprior, in hunc quaſi Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae ſubverſorem, omnium odia telaque ſine reſpectu, contor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebantur.</hi> If any of their Kings were more milde or meek, and ſomewhat neerer to the truth, all their hatreds and darts were caſt againſt him without reſpect, as the ſubverter of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany.</hi> How true of thoſe is that which was long ſince ſaid of the King of <hi>England,</hi> that he was <hi>Rex diabolorum?</hi> O that we all knew, and duely conſidered, what a <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> what a <hi>divine leaven of life and righteouſneſs,</hi> what a <hi>cement of love and unity,</hi> what a <hi>binding chord reconciling of all jarring diſſonancies and differences,</hi> our good God hath ſent among us, (as appeares by all his <hi>Proclamations,</hi> and eſpecially his late <hi>Declaration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Eccleſiaſtical Affaires,</hi> in all which breathes a ſpirit of life and righteouſneſs, love, unity, and peace,) that we might walk worthy of him! Then would the divided <hi>Parties</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter know,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>6. <hi>How they may be perſwaded unto peace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have our <hi>gracious Kings eminent example,</hi> who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>umpires theſe very differences</hi> between the <hi>divided parties;</hi> which is the property <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>wiſe and good prince. It is true that <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Uſurpers</hi> in all Ages have bin wont either
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65679:28"/>to <hi>find,</hi> or <hi>make</hi> and nouriſh <hi>Differences</hi> among the people, that their emulations and animoſities being ſpent upon their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite reſpective Factions, they might have no leiſure to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or diſturb the ſecurity of their Oppreſſors; as a certain Player at <hi>Rome,</hi> when the <hi>Pretor</hi> asked him of what profeſſion he was, told him, That he was one of them, <hi>who whyl'd the populacy, that they might not have time to conſider, prevent, and hinder his knavery.</hi> Upon this ground <hi>Machiavel</hi> taught his Scholars this Leſſon, <hi>Divide, &amp; impera;</hi> Divide, and rule: He had lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned this Maxime of his Tutor the great <hi>Abadden</hi> and <hi>Apollyon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Quite contrary hath been the practice of all good <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>Governors,</hi> and our Soveraigns, one of the beſt of them, to aſſimilate their people, and render them like unto themſelves in <hi>vertuous and holy life,</hi> and ſo to rule them <hi>in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, peace and concord.</hi> And what <hi>enmity</hi> they cheriſh among their Subjects, its no other than what they learned of their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> the <hi>King of kings, who</hi> put <hi>enmity between the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent,</hi> even <hi>the Law of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> Epheſ. 2. whereby they may become enemies to ſin and iniquity. And this <hi>enmity</hi> drives out the ſin, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus qui turbat omnia,</hi> which breaks all <hi>peace</hi> with God and man. Happy, thrice happy they who enure themſelves unto ſuch <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> as is wholly exerciſed upon the <hi>enemies of their own houſe!</hi> Such reflex actions guided by divine wiſdom, rend to the ſubduing of our brutiſh affections. Such <hi>enmity</hi> is ſafe, while it is employed at home; but when it breaks forth of doors, and becomes directed by the <hi>earthly, ſenſual, divelliſh wiſdom,</hi> what ever the pretence may be, it tends to <hi>confuſion and every evil work;</hi> as he who aimed at a <hi>beast,</hi> but ſlew a <hi>man.</hi> Such <hi>fire</hi> is ſafe and ſerviceable on the <hi>hearth,</hi> but what is more unſafe, more deſtructive, what devours and conſumes more, when it comes abroad?</p>
               <p>We have heard how <hi>exemplary the King</hi> is in this very buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And how powerful ſuch a royal leader is, may appear by that almoſt proverbial verſe,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus componitur orbis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:65679:29"/>
Th' whole world's compos'd to th' patern of a King.</l>
               </q>
               <p>How much more prevalent ought his <hi>precept</hi> and <hi>example</hi> to be with us, where the <hi>King of kings,</hi> whom <hi>our King and all other good Kings</hi> own as their <hi>Soveraign?</hi> He it is who is the <hi>Author of Peace and Lover of Concord, the God of peace, Phil.</hi> 4.9. The Son of God is the <hi>Prince of peace, Eſay</hi> 9.6. His principal <hi>type</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> is <hi>Jedidiah the beloved of the Lord, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the <hi>peaceable,</hi> as his names ſpeak him, and ſuch was his <hi>reign.</hi> His principal <hi>type</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> was the <hi>peaceable Melchiſedec,</hi> the <hi>prieſt of peace,</hi> yea the King of it, King of Salem, which is King of peace, <hi>Hebr</hi> 7.2. His <hi>Prophets</hi> are the <hi>Meſſengers of peace, Eſay</hi> 25. His <hi>Argels</hi> firſt proclamed <hi>peace, Luke</hi> 2. His <hi>Apoſtles and Miniſters</hi> are the preachers of peace. His Goſpel which they preached, is the Goſpel of <hi>peace, Epheſ.</hi> 6.15. His <hi>way</hi> is the <hi>way of peace, Luke</hi> 1.79. He himſelf is the <hi>preacher of peace, Epheſ.</hi> 2. the <hi>peace-maker,</hi> yea the very <hi>eſſential peace it ſelf, Eph.</hi> 2.14. Thus <hi>God the Father by his Son, his Argels, his Prophets, his Apoſtles, his Miniſters</hi> promote this <hi>Common peace</hi> among men. And his <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>end</hi> is the very higheſt, <hi>Union and Communion with himſelf in his divine nature;</hi> For which the Son of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayes in behalt both of his <hi>Apoſtles, John</hi> 17.2.19. and of all thoſe who ſhall believe on him through their word, that they may be <hi>one even as the Father and Son are one,</hi> 20, 21, 22. This is that glorious <hi>end</hi> whereat God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf aimes in his <hi>precepts of pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> that we may be <hi>par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>akers of Chriſt, Heb.</hi> 3.14. That we may be <hi>partakers and communican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in the divine nature</hi> it ſelf, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 14. <hi>That our fellowſhip may be with the Father and his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 1.3. <hi>That God may be all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo high <hi>aimes</hi> are at the advancement of our <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſhould we be wanting to our ſelves in the endeavoring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo great a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> as the <hi>Bleſſing of Peace?</hi> It is the firſt good teſtimony wherewith we finde the Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they were <hi>peaceable. Theſe men are peaceable among us, Gen.</hi> 34.21. And the <hi>Primitive ſpiritual Sons of</hi> Jacob were wondred at, <hi>See how the Chriſtians love one another.</hi> Nor is there any thing ſo much wanting to the felicity of this church
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65679:29"/>
                  <hi>the Iſrael of God in this nation,</hi> as the true inheriting theſe <hi>two testimonies of Love and Peace,</hi> which invite and draw down the <hi>Bleſſing of everlaſting Life, Love, and Peace.</hi> For <hi>where brethren dwell together in unity, there the Lord commanded that his Bleſſing and Life for evermore.</hi> Nor is there any doubt, but were we united in <hi>love</hi> and <hi>peace, the Spirit of life, love, and peace would be upon us. For the promiſe is made to thoſe who were then afar off,</hi> as we are, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Conſider this <hi>Idea,</hi> this <hi>Image of life, love, and peace,</hi> and look inwardly into thy ſelf who ever thou art, <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> whether thou finde it living in thee. Conſider the <hi>patern,</hi> and be aſhamed of thy <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ambition,</hi> thy <hi>ſtrife</hi> and <hi>contention.</hi> And remember its required in that myſtical Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance touching the Goſpel-Prieſthood, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.14. That all the <hi>Priests</hi> of the Lord <hi>be the ſons of Zadoc,</hi> not ſuch <hi>ſons of Zadoc</hi> who were <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who deny the reſurrection, and the reward of the Juſt in the life to come, but <hi>juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous perſons;</hi> ſuch as the ſons of <hi>Zadoc,</hi> humble and lowly, not proud, not ambitious, not contending <hi>who ſhould ſeem to be the greatest.</hi> The ſons of <hi>Zadoc</hi> are <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>true</hi> in what ever they ſpeak. They are merciful and compaſſionate, liberal and bountiful, full of almſ-deeds, lovers of hoſpitality, lovers of good things and good men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate. Such muſt <hi>the ſons of</hi> Zadoc <hi>be,</hi> that they may be like unto that true <hi>Zadoc,</hi> that <hi>Just One,</hi> Acts 22.14. <hi>that humble, faithful, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful High Priest,</hi> Heb. 2.17.</p>
               <p>For indeed why (my brethren of the Presbytery) ſhould we above all other Parties, and divided Judgements, be the moſt ambitious of <hi>ruling</hi> over others? Is it our <hi>learning that puffs us up?</hi> There are, no doubt, many <hi>Learned men</hi> among us in our way: yet are there alſo many, whom we oppoſe, not inferior to us in the knowledge of the Scriptures, to ſay no more. Or is it our <hi>obedience</hi> to what we know, that makes us ſeem to our ſelves better then other men, and worthy to <hi>govern</hi> them? (For pride is a worm that ſometime breeds even in the <hi>trees of righteouſneſs,</hi> Eſay 61.3.) Surely ſome of thoſe, whom many of us moſt deſpiſe, have more <hi>underſtanding</hi> of ſpiritual things,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65679:30"/>and are more humble, more ſelf-denying, more patient, more obedient unto the Truth, then the moſt of us are. And in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they muſt be ſo: For they who aim at the <hi>perfect life,</hi> and <hi>believe it poſſible</hi> to be obtained, they muſt have the <hi>life mere abundantly,</hi> then they who <hi>believe it to be impoſſible,</hi> as the moſt of us do. Becauſe <hi>belief</hi> graſps and lays hold on the <hi>power,</hi> Eſay 27. and <hi>hope</hi> is the ground of all <hi>endeavor:</hi> where therefore there is no ſuch <hi>belief</hi> or <hi>hope</hi> of the <hi>perfect life,</hi> there can be no <hi>earnest endeavor</hi> to obtain the ſame. The greater <hi>endeavor,</hi> the greater is the attainment; as he who aims at the <hi>Sun,</hi> ſhoots higher than he who aims at the <hi>Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or is it your <hi>wealth,</hi> or <hi>ſtrength,</hi> or confidence in the <hi>joynt-Commonwealth-intereſt,</hi> which you inveigled long ſince into your party, which raiſeth your <hi>ambition?</hi> They have found, that ſhould you compaſs your <hi>grand deſign,</hi> it would not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the <hi>blood and treaſure</hi> which hath been already ſpent in vain. They reſt ſatisfied that your miſplaced zeal hath unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them; ſo that they judge it much more ſafe to expiate that errour, whereinto you lead them, then to engage in a new, leſt the latter prove worſe then the former.</p>
               <p>Beſides, are you not aware, how little warrant you have from the holy Scriptures for any ſuch enterprize? Doth not that oracle flie in your faces, which at other times is much in your mouthes, <hi>not by might, nor by power, but by my ſpirit?</hi> ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
               <p>Do you not perceive that ſo doing, you ſhould not truſt in the <hi>true God,</hi> but in your <hi>Mammon? You cannot ſerve both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> Nay, ſhould you not <hi>forſake the Lord of hoſts,</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the God of forces?</hi> Dan. 11.38.</p>
               <p>Or have you ſuch power, think you, with the <hi>rude multitude,</hi> that ye can by them promiſe your ſelves advancement of your cauſe? Or can you hope for like <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſperous</hi> ſucceſs (if it can be call'd <hi>proſperous,</hi> which is founded on <hi>Ataxy, Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi>) that a <hi>prime Reformer</hi> of yours boaſted of, when he, by inſinuations with the <hi>populacy,</hi> had changed the <hi>Government</hi> of a certain City, <hi>Hac faece hom num evicimus?</hi> By theſe dregs of men, ſaith he, <hi>we obtained our purpoſe.</hi> Believe it, they are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65679:30"/>become ſo wiſe <hi>by coſtly and bloody experience,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that, as by a <hi>ſtratagem in war,</hi> they will not be deceived a <hi>ſecond time.</hi> For although there may be ſome ignorant <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots;</hi> who are lead by your <hi>purſe-ſtrings,</hi> or <hi>example,</hi> or <hi>counſel,</hi> or <hi>intreaty,</hi> and others who know no better thing, may <hi>follow you in their ſimplicity;</hi> Yet the generality of the people being ſenſible onely of an <hi>outward auſterity</hi> and <hi>formal pretenſion of Godlineſs</hi> without any conviction of <hi>inward power and efficacy,</hi> they will not hazzard a <hi>cut finger</hi> for the advancement of your <hi>Government.</hi> Yea, ſome wiſe men conceive, that you would not ſo eagerly oppoſe the <hi>antient Government</hi> of the Church with your <hi>novelty,</hi> but that you fear your <hi>former bold enterprizes</hi> would not be ſafe, without attempting ſomewhat thats worſe—<hi>Brevibus Gyaris aut carcere dignum.</hi> Or, that by indulgence and favour, you may come off, among thoſe of your party, with the reputation of reſolute and <hi>conſcientious men.</hi> Or, that ſome principal <hi>ſticklers</hi> and <hi>leaders</hi> among you may have their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience better informed with a Deanary or Biſhoprick.</hi> Or, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are ſome unquiet and unpeaceable ſpirits among you, who conceive that Atheiſm, <hi>profaneneſs, impiety,</hi> and all irreligion would violently break into the <hi>Church,</hi> unleſs they <hi>ſtood in the gap</hi> to keep it out. Alas, Good men! They are like thoſe little woodden ſtatues which are ſet under the main beames of an <hi>houſe,</hi> with very piteous faces, as if they bare up the <hi>whole building,</hi> whereas indeed, were they taken away, <hi>the houſe</hi> would ſtand very well without them.</p>
               <p>But what is their pretence? They conceive the <hi>Chriſtian faith</hi> is in hazzard, and would be loſt, if they ſtood not up in defence of it. And therefore they alledge <hi>ſcripture</hi> for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their <hi>contention, that they may ſin by the Book.</hi> For why? They ought, as they ſay, to <hi>contend for the faith that once was given to the Saints, Jude</hi> verſe 3. That is (ſaith the Gloſs of the Quarto Bible,) <hi>againſt the aſſaults of Satan and Hereticks.</hi> Whence ſome gather, that they ſhould <hi>ſtrive with others</hi> for the <hi>Apoſtolical faith.</hi> But in reaſon; men ought firſt to <hi>contend for the faith once given to the Saints,</hi> that it might be <hi>in themſelves,</hi> viz. <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt the wiſdom of God, and power of God,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65679:31"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, That <hi>faith,</hi> that is, the <hi>obedience of faith,</hi> as Rom. 1. and 16. That <hi>victorious faith which overcomes the world.</hi> 1 John 5.4. Whereas therefore ſome then, as at this day, had brought in a <hi>lazy kinde of imagination,</hi> which they called <hi>faith, that Chriſt had done, and ſuffered all things for them;</hi> and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ungodly, and turned the <hi>grace of God into wantonneſs,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſinned, that grace might abound;</hi> And ſo <hi>they denyed the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the onely Lord, when they obeyed other Lords,</hi> as Eſay 26. And pretended impotency, weakneſs, and inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do the will of our onely Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Theſe <hi>Jude</hi> exhorted to <hi>contend</hi> for the true <hi>faith</hi> once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Saints. For had we the <hi>true faith, which was once given to the Saints,</hi> it would no doubt empower us againſt all <hi>ungodlineſs, and all wantonneſs, yea all the luſt of the fleſh, luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life; which are all that is in the world.</hi> 1 John 2.16. And the true <hi>faith is the victory that overcomes that world,</hi> 1. John 5.4. Which <hi>faith,</hi> were it in us, it would overcome <hi>that pride of life,</hi> whence comes this contention, who ſhould ſeem to be the greateſt.</p>
               <p>But they will have no <hi>Peace,</hi> they ſay, without <hi>Truth.</hi> This is an old juggle, whereby the credulous and ignorant multitude were ſeduced into the late War, and ſo perſwaded to believe a lie. Not but that <hi>peace</hi> is, and ought to be joyned with <hi>truth,</hi> as <hi>Zech.</hi> 8 16.19. and elſewhere. But is not <hi>peace</hi> alſo found coupled with <hi>righteouſneſs?</hi> Eſay 32.17. and with <hi>holineſs,</hi> Heb 12.14. and <hi>love,</hi> Pſalm 119.165. and <hi>purity,</hi> James 3.17. And what <hi>Truth</hi> is that which is joyned with <hi>Peace?</hi> Is it not notoriouſly known, that they are wont to call their <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Opinions</hi> which they have choſen to hold, by the glorious name of <hi>Truth,</hi> according to which they account themſelves, and would be accounted by others, <hi>Orthodox?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But doth not our Lord Jeſus call <hi>himſelf The Truth?</hi> John 14.6. Now mark what kinde of <hi>Truth</hi> the Lord Jeſus is, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians 4.20. <hi>Ye have not ſo learnt Christ, if at least ye have heard him, and have been taught in him, as the Truth is in Jeſus, that ye put off according to the former converſation, the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lusts, and be renewed in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65679:31"/>ſpirit of your minde; and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs and holineſs of Truth.</hi> Whence follows <hi>truth</hi> in ſpeech, wherefore putting away <hi>the lie, ſpeak ye every one truth to his neighbor, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>truth</hi> they had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to whom St. <hi>John</hi> wrote, 1 John 2.21. <hi>I have not written unto you, becauſe ye know not the truth, but becauſe ye know it, and that no l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is of the truth.</hi> This is the <hi>Truth</hi> unto which the true <hi>Peace</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyned, and without which there is no <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, beloved Brethren, let us beware, leſt under what pretence ſoever, we break the <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> either of which ought to be more dear unto us than our own lives. Let us take heed, O let us adviſedly, ſeriouſly, and timely take heed, brethren, leſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the practiſe of Chriſt, and the holy Apoſtles, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtom of the unbelieving Jews and Heathens, and ſome Zealors of our own, we go about to <hi>reform the world.</hi> It was ſaid of the Lord Jeſus, that <hi>he perverted the Nation, when he converted it;</hi> and of the Apoſtles, <hi>that they turned the world upſide down;</hi> when, by the weapons of their ſpiritual warfare, they caſt down imaginations, and every high thing that exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and exalted the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and meekneſs of Jeſus Chriſt. They never went about to <hi>reform a people, by raiſing Riots, Routs,</hi> and <hi>Tumults.</hi> They were not the Apoſtles, but the <hi>unbelieving Jews, who moved with envy, took unto them certain lewd fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a company, and ſet all the City in an uproar,</hi> Acts 17.5.</p>
               <p>Let us beware, beloved Brethren, leſt we go about to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Church,</hi> as the woman did when ſhe ſought her groat, according to an old falſe reading of the vulgar Tranſlation, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8. <hi>evertit domum,</hi> ſhe <hi>overturned the houſe,</hi> when ſhe ſhould have onely <hi>ſwept it,</hi> according to the true reading <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit domum.</hi> For ſurely the wiſe woman, the Church, ſeeking the <hi>Lords image</hi> loſt in his Coin <hi>[Man,]</hi> by the <hi>light of the Lords Candle,</hi> which is <hi>his Spirit,</hi> Prov. 20.27. ſhe ſweeps and cleanſes the houſe from <hi>all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, until ſhe finde her Lords image in righteouſneſs and holineſs of Truth,</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65679:32"/>ſo becomes reformed and renewed in the ſpirit of her minde.</p>
               <p>This, this is the <hi>true Reformation of the Church,</hi> not <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning it;</hi> as <hi>Bertius</hi> ſaith we do, when we go about to <hi>reform it.</hi> O let us prove him a falſe prophet, who hath theſe words in his <hi>Breviarum totius Orbis terrarum,</hi> page 7. <hi>Habent hoc pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>prium Calvanistae, ut ſtatum in quem irrepſerunt, evertant, neque ante conquieſcant quam ipſi rerum potiantur. Irriſores, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulenti, factioſi, diſputaces, ingrati, arrogantes ſupra quam dici aut credi poteſt, hoſtes Catholicorum juratiſſimi, quique non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ipſi nihil conferunt ad repellendam imminentem Chriſtianorum cervicibus Turcarum vim; ſed etiam motis inteſtinis diſſidiis belliſque impediu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t alios Reges id conantes, quin &amp; opes vireſque ipſorum à communi hoste averſas in mutuam Chriſtiano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciem concitant. Atque hoc ipſis est reformare Eccleſiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall leave this upon your <hi>ſpirits</hi> ſadly to be thought upon; and ſpeak a word unto my Brethren of <hi>Epiſcopal perſwaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know many of you, beloved Brethren, and I believe here are far many more in this and our neighbor Nation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> eminent in wiſdom and piety, men of profound learning, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, grave, juſt, prudent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who have been refined and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the <hi>furnace of humiliation,</hi> and are come forth as <hi>veſſels</hi> of honor fit for their Maſters uſe. Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, perſons who hae far tranſcended the envy of their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And having been turned into ſtrange Countreys, have declar'd evidently what difference there is between <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one <hi>unlearned</hi> and <hi>learned.</hi> Unto theſe I ſay onely, <hi>Macti eſtote,</hi> proceed and ſhine forth as lights of the Church.</p>
               <p>To you I ſpeak, who have been <hi>Sufferers</hi> alſo, but, if report not onely of your enemies, but even of your friends alſo wrong you not, ſome of you have not improved your ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to the advantage of your own ſouls, or the Church of God, ſo that you cannot truly and experimentally ſay, <hi>It is good for us that we have been afflicted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are not many of you returned the very ſame men you were, onely worſe, as being more heightned with pride, more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bittered with envy, more enflamed with wrath, more enlarged with deſire of revenge?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65679:32"/>
                  <hi>Atqui cum peccata carnalia plus habeant infamiae, ſpiritualia plus de natura peccati, (quod ſanctus Gregorius ait) Ut fama veſtrae parcam, Latine vos pacciis alloquar. Aiunt è vobis eſſe, (at ſpero eos admodum paucos eſſe) qui ventri nimium indulgent, mutuo ſe poculis provecant, invitant ſe pluſculum, &amp;c. An non hoc idem ipſum vitium est, quod pientiſſimus Rex haud feret in eajulo, haud feret in treſſi agaſone? Anidem ipſum tulerit in Miniſtro Dei? An non etiam vos illi feciales, qui contra haec fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitia moreſque vitioſes, prudentiſſimi Regis inimicitias indicitis? Qua fronte utcunque caperata inhibetis illud, quod vita licentiori comprobatis? Pudet haec opprobria vobis, Et dici potuiſſe &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are ye they who <hi>are come out of that great tribulation?</hi> Rev. 7.14. ſhould not then <hi>your garments be made white in the blood of the Lamb?</hi> Should not you be planted in the likeneſs of his death, and ſo be made alſo like unto him in his pure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and ſpotleſs life and reſurrection? So ſhould you be fit to ſay in way of thankfulneſs, with that Heavenly Quire, <hi>Bleſsing and glory, and wiſdom, and thanksgiving, and honor, and power, and might, be unto our God for ever and ever! Amen.</hi> This is an <hi>heaventy Doxology</hi> when the <hi>heavenly life</hi> ſpeaks it. Otherwiſe an unholy, debaucht, and vicious life is the greateſt ingratitude, eſpecially in a Prieſt.</p>
               <p>For what honor, what glory can be to God, what profit is it unto you or to the Church of God, that <hi>holy hands have been laid upon you</hi> and that you be made <hi>Prieſts,</hi> if by a ſinful life you diſhonor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od and that holy function, and render your ſelves unfit for the diſcharge of it? Flatter not your ſelves, not pleaſe your ſelves in that honorable name of <hi>Prieſts;</hi> and that thereby you have power to binde and looſe, ſo that whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained. Do you conſider what that worthy name imports? Is not a <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſuch an one as is growen up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>old age of Chriſt?</hi> Epheſ. 4. And dare you in your <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> while yet you are ſubject to the ſins incident unto the <hi>ſpiritual child-hood,</hi> and before you are ſo ſtrong as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the evil one, dare you aſſume to your ſelves the power
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65679:33"/>of binding and looſing, even while you your ſelves are bound with the chaines of your own ſins? Can you think that ſuch great works as are binding and looſing, are annexed to your <hi>perſons,</hi> or to the <hi>due qualifications of the Prieſthood,</hi> and ſuch as ought to be in you? There is no doubt, but, as the <hi>Prieſt</hi> under the law, had skill to put difference between <hi>holy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, and clean and unclean,</hi> which he could not do, if he drank wine or ſtrong drink, before he went into the Tabernacle of the congregation, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. ſo neither can the <hi>Goſpel Prieſt</hi> diſcern between <hi>holy and unholy, righteouſneſs and unrighteouſneſs, pure and unpure,</hi> ſo as to <hi>bind or looſe,</hi> if he be <hi>drunk with wine wherein is exceſs,</hi> or drunk, and not with wine, <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.9. as with the ſpirit of opinion.</p>
               <p>O my beloved brethren, the <hi>Goſpel Prieſt</hi> muſt well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of ſin and corruption, and temptation unto ſin, and the devices of Satan, and meanes and ways how to eſcape them; He is the <hi>ſpiritual man who judgeth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.15. <hi>Who knowes the mind of the Lord,</hi> Rom. 11.34. <hi>Who hath the mind of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. ult. Such a <hi>Prieſt</hi> is able and fit to <hi>binde and looſe,</hi> as having received the ſpirit of God, and been endued with power from above. Otherwiſe its great boldneſs, and preſumption for any man to aſſume ſuch power unto himſelf. And what, my Brethren, emboldens you here unto? Becauſe, you ſay, you are made <hi>Prieſts:</hi> And therefore you preſume to take the Apoſtles authority for your patern, to whom the Lord Jeſus ſaid, <hi>Thoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> John 20.23. O when ſhall we deal ſincerely and impartially with the holy Scriptures! How often do men cite the divine teſtimonies, as the devil alledged part of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 91.11, 12. to our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 4.6. Where he leaves out what was moſt neceſſary to be underſtood? And in this caſe of great moment, men do the very ſame; For where our Lord ſaith, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted, &amp;c.</hi> he premiſeth thoſe words, <hi>Receive the Holy Chost.</hi> And then immediately follow choſe other, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> They therefore who have
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65679:33"/>received the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God, are the fit men for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Goſpel-Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, my Brethren, boaſt not of your <hi>power,</hi> but rather pray unto the Lord for his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> whereby you may be impowered; For our Heavenly Father will not fail to give his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> unto thoſe his children who ask him, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. and are obedient unto him, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.32.</p>
               <p>Nor can the <hi>Book of Common-prayer,</hi> though full fraught with <hi>Divine Petitions and Praiſes of God,</hi> nor your dayly reading of it, render you <hi>divine,</hi> or, as ye are called, <hi>Divines,</hi> unleſs your ſelves have a <hi>ſhare</hi> of what you pray for. Do ye not pray, <hi>that we may hereafter</hi> (that is, after the Confeſſion of ſins) <hi>live a godly, righteous, and ſober life, to the glory of Gods holy Name?</hi> And in the Communion-ſervice, do not you put up unto God this large Petition? <hi>That we may ever hereafter ſerve and pleaſe him in newneſs of life, to the honor and glory of his Name, through Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi> Yea, do you not pray every day, <hi>that we may fall into no ſin, nor run into any kinde of danger, but that all our doings may be ordered by his governance, to do always that which is righteous in his ſight, through Jeſus Christ our Lord?</hi> Is your <hi>charity</hi> more fervent toward others, than toward your ſelves, Brethren? Or is your <hi>endeavor</hi> leſs in behalf of your ſelves, than in behalf of others? Do you pray, that they may live a <hi>godly, righteous, and ſober life; that they may ever ſerve and pleaſe God in newneſs of life; that they may fall into no ſin; that they may do always that which is righteous in the Lords ſight, &amp;c.</hi> and do you not pray for all theſe things in behalf of your ſelves? If ſo, whence is the complaint that <hi>theſe things</hi> are not found in you? that you have but a <hi>ſmall part</hi> of them? For if you prayed for them ſo, that your ſelves might be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of them, there is no doubt but our good God would grant your requeſts, becauſe they are according to his will; <hi>Now this is the confidence that we have in him, that if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us. And if we know that he hear us, whatſoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions which we deſired of him,</hi> 1 John 5.14, 15.</p>
               <p>Yea, and becauſe you pray not for your ſelves, it is much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65679:34"/>to be feared, that your Prayers are not heard for others. For in this ſenſe the Proverb is good and true, <hi>That Charity begins at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the ground of another Complaint, <hi>That the Common-prayer is reſorted unto by many looſe and debaucht per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> (and I believe it is as true, that many cloſe hypocrites reſort unto <hi>conceived prayers.</hi>) And hence ariſeth one of the Presbyterians Invectives againſt the <hi>Book of Common-prayer,</hi> that (like as St. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſons againſt the weakneſs of the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law,</hi> Heb. 10.1.) it cannot make the comers thereunto perfect. Not that they think it poſſible, that any one ſhould be perfect in this life, by what ever power God gives a man (their own words in their large Catechiſm) though Chriſt and his Apoſtles enjoyn us <hi>to be perfect;</hi> and <hi>Epaphras</hi> prayeth for the Coloſſians, <hi>that they might ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God,</hi> Coloſ. 4.12. But this is the Presbyterians <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum ad hominem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit this cannot be imputed unto the <hi>Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer,</hi> that it cannot render men <hi>perfect:</hi> For the defect is not in the <hi>prayers,</hi> which are in commenſuration even to the <hi>higheſt perfection,</hi> as elſewhere, ſo eſpecially where the Church prayeth, <hi>that we may perfectly love God, and worthyly magnifie his holy name.</hi> But indeed the great defect is in the <hi>Comers thereunto;</hi> or many of them, who, without due conſideration of either <hi>prayers or praiſes,</hi> turn them over their tongues care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and negligently, as if the very hearing and reciting of theſe prayers were the onely true and perfect ſervice of God, and think, he is pleaſed with ſuch a performance of it, and ſo they reſt in it <hi>tanquam in opere operato.</hi> Yea, I have heard it alledged, that the <hi>Common-prayer</hi> is that <hi>pure offering</hi> whereof the Lord ſpeakes, as to be fulfilled among the Gentiles, Mal. 1.11. <hi>In every place incenſe ſhall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely by Incenſe, Prayer is underſtood, according to <hi>Pſalus</hi> 141.2. But the pure offering is little underſtood, and leſs practiſed, even the <hi>dayly ſacrifice of mortification</hi> which is taken away according to <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.11, 12, 13. &amp; 11.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65679:34"/>
Truly what is generally ſpoken, may be applied more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the Book of Common-prayer, <hi>Quaeneglecta vileſcunt, eadem ſi conſiderentur, habentur admiratione.</hi> The method of the Liturgy, the Prayers and Praiſes of God in it, becauſe neglected by Presbyters, yea, and by many Epiſcopals them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are not eſteemed; but if, according to their weight and moment, they were duly conſidered (ſome offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being removed) they would provoke pious men of both parties even to admire them.</p>
               <p>So that the principal thing that's wanting to the Honor of God, the good of his Church, and the due eſtimation of the Book of Common-prayer, is the Chriſtian life which is required out of it. This, my brethren, procures authority to your Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, veneration to your outward Divine Service, and due reſpect unto your Perſons. Without which, neither a Long Caſſock, nor a Broad Girdle, nor affected Gravity of Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will avayl any thing at all, among wiſe and good men. <hi>Ad populum phaleras</hi>—</p>
               <p>Not that theſe are deſpicable, as ſome vain and ignorant men have thought them, but indeed venerable, if we conſider what they import; as we ſhall underſtand, if we remember our <hi>vow in our Baptiſm,</hi> which I fear, the moſt of us forget, <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>abremutation of Satan and all his works,</hi> &amp;c. which in the antient Church was expreſſed by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Satan. And belief of the Goſpel, and all the articles of the Chriſtian faith, and the keeping of Gods commandments;</hi> all which were comprized in the oppoſite phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I enroll my ſelf in Christs Matricula, or Military Roll.</hi> So that the Chriſtian Profeſſion is a kind of <hi>warfare;</hi> and the perſon <hi>baptized</hi> promiſeth to continue Chriſts faithful Soldier and ſervant unto his lives end. And this is that which the <hi>Priest</hi> holds forth in his <hi>Sagum</hi> or <hi>Caſſock,</hi> which was <hi>Veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum militare,</hi> a military Garment, and ſo uſed by the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, ſaith <hi>Tacitus;</hi> and it is the ſame which is in uſe among moſt Soldiers at this day. <hi>Plutarch</hi> calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Soldiers garment,</hi> which, ſaith <hi>Nomius,</hi> he wore above all his other apparel; a figure of Charity which muſt be put on above
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65679:35"/>other, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. And becauſe <hi>love muſt be ſincere,</hi> Rom. 12.9. the Chriſtian Soldier muſt be <hi>girded</hi> with the <hi>girdle of Truth,</hi> Eph. 4.15. &amp; 6.14. For the <hi>Girdle</hi> was a part of the Roman Soldiers armour, <hi>Cingulum militare,</hi> the Soldiers Belt, <hi>a quo arma dependent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidor,</hi> whereon his other weapons hung. Yea, when the Iſraelites came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> it's ſaid, <hi>Exodus</hi> 13.18. they went up <hi>harneſſed;</hi> the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is properly <hi>accincti,</hi> girded, importing thus much, That the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God going up out of the <hi>Spiritual Egypt,</hi> muſt be <hi>armed</hi> with the whole armour of God, eſpecially with the <hi>Girdle of truth, faithfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſincerity;</hi> as alſo with <hi>ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 18.39. and with <hi>chaſtity,</hi> wherewith the Lord implies his Spouſe ſhould be <hi>girded,</hi> Jer 13.11.</p>
               <p>O my Brethren, both of Epiſcopal and of Presbyterian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion! conſider, and be hearily aſhamed of your common error, that ye have both been ſo groſly miſtaken, that ye have neglected the <hi>common enemy,</hi> even the Devil, againſt whom we are all engaged by our Vow in Baptiſm, and deſerted the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe of Chriſtianity, <hi>the crucifying of the old man,</hi> and are fallen foul one upon another. Do you know no better the <hi>devices of Satan?</hi> Are you ſo little known to your ſelves, that you take no notice of your <hi>lusts that war in your members?</hi> Do you no more regard them who are without? What opinion, think you, hath the religious, and irreligious world of you? Remember, the Cauſe you are engaged in, is the Cauſe of God: you have entred covenant with him upon theſe terms, that you ſhould <hi>fight againſt the world, the fleſh, and the devil.</hi> The Cauſe is <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi> and muſt needs be <hi>good.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calls it ſo. <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.12. It's a <hi>Cauſe</hi> wherein all the people of God have been engaged from the beginning, even ſince the Lord <hi>put enmity between the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent,</hi> and promiſed, <hi>that the holy ſeed Chriſt ſhould break the ſerpents head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> Let not the old ſubtile Serpent any longer beguile you, who deceives the Nations. <hi>Quit your ſelves like men.</hi> Lay down your <hi>Enmity</hi> one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and joyn all your forces, and all your courage againſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65679:35"/>the <hi>common enemy:</hi> and ſo <hi>the God of Peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mean time let us enquire into the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the things which make for Peace,</hi> and</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>7. <hi>By what means Reconciliation may be made between the divided Parties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Divine Life,</hi> the effect whereof is <hi>Peace,</hi> is diſcovered to St. <hi>John,</hi> Revel. 21. and every one who is <hi>willing,</hi> is invited thereunto. But its vain labour to diſcover the <hi>life,</hi> which is above to the wiſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Pro. 15.24. unleſs we have a <hi>Jacobs Ladder,</hi> whereby we may aſcend thereunto. This we may do by divers <hi>ſteps</hi> or <hi>means;</hi> which are either ſuch as <hi>remove obſtructions out of the way of peace,</hi> or ſuch as <hi>poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direct our feet into that way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as the <hi>godly life</hi> is a neceſſary means for the obtaining the <hi>eternal life and peace,</hi> which is <hi>homogeneal,</hi> and of the ſame nature with it; ſo is the <hi>death unto ſin</hi> a neceſſary means of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the <hi>godly life,</hi> as the Apoſtle reaſons, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. when <hi>Chriſt, which is our life, ſhall appear, then ſhall we appear with him in glory; mortifie therefore your earthly members,</hi> whence it is that ſinful men are ſaid <hi>not to know the way of peace,</hi> Rom. 3.17. And who can direct us better into <hi>this</hi> way, than he who is the <hi>Prince of Life,</hi> Acts 5. <hi>And prince of peace,</hi> Eſay 9. who appeared <hi>the Day-ſpring from on high to viſit us, to give light to them that ſit in darkneſs, and the ſhadow of death, and to guide our feet into the way of peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into this way he leads us by <hi>precept</hi> and <hi>example.</hi> By <hi>precept</hi> of <hi>humility,</hi> and <hi>lowlineſs of mind, by ſelf denyal, and taking up the croſs dayly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humility</hi> is the firſt ſtep toward <hi>Mortification,</hi> and that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream neceſſary, becauſe <hi>pride</hi> the contrary hereunto <hi>obſtructs the way of Peace,</hi> Pro. 13.10. <hi>For onely by pride cometh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi> And if onely by <hi>pride,</hi> whence, I beſeech you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the <hi>preſent contentions</hi> among us? Is it not becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, every one would be greateſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65679:36"/>
Truly a very ſtrange thing it is, that men eminent for <hi>learning,</hi> and profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſhould ſo openly ſpend their <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>heat</hi> about that <hi>old diſpute,</hi> who ſhould be the greateſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 'Tis true, this <hi>Controverſie</hi> was among the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> but they had not yet received the <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi> which I deſire both parties adviſedly to conſider. Why ſhould they not rather endeavour after the faireſt object of <hi>emulation,</hi> the onely lawful <hi>contention, who ſhould be the beſt?</hi> The <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> herein condemn too many of us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who were wont to exerciſe their Children in ſuch <hi>queſtions</hi> as theſe, who in all <hi>Sparta</hi> was the <hi>moſt ſober, moſt juſt, moſt prudent, moſt valiant man,</hi> &amp;c. And it was one of them who ſay, <hi>Nemo me major niſi qui me melior;</hi> No man is greater then I, unleſs he be better then I am. Yea, although I doubt not, but the main deſign of the Covenant was <hi>outing</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Inning of</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in their room, yet in the cloſe of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> by an over-ruling hand, the Covenanters vow, <hi>That our true and unfeigned purpoſe, deſire and endeavor, for our ſelves, and all under our power and charge, both in publick and private, in all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the example of real Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This cloſe of the <hi>Covenant</hi> which is moſt conſonant unto the word of God, hath been, I fear, quite forgotten, and the main endeavour hath been <hi>to go one before another</hi> in <hi>wealth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor;</hi> as for the <hi>endeavour, and ſtrife to exceed one another, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our duties toward God and man,</hi> O how modeſt moſt men are! O how eaſily doth every man yield to another to go before him!</p>
               <p>Yet if any man, according to the <hi>Covenant,</hi> endeavor to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed others in <hi>goodneſs,</hi> (who have bound up themſelves by their principles, which they reſolve not to exceed) if he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to be <hi>perfect as our heavenly Father is perfect,</hi> he is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at leaſt <hi>erroneous in his judgement,</hi> if he can eſcape the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diners ſheers of Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>cutting off,</hi> for preſuming to <hi>grow in grace</hi> above his neighbors.</p>
               <p>The <hi>contention is not who ſhould be the beſt man,</hi> but who ſhould be the <hi>greatest.</hi> And <hi>onely from pride comes this contention.</hi> And
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65679:36"/>this is a great part of <hi>ſelf</hi> which is to be <hi>denyed.</hi> That's the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> ſtep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Self-denyal.</hi> There are in man ſince the <hi>fall,</hi> the <hi>abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of three ſelfs!</hi> One whereby he agrees with the <hi>beaſt,</hi> and lives according to the principles of <hi>brutiſh man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Another whereby he agrees with the <hi>old fubtil ſcrpent,</hi> which deceiveth all the world with falſe principles of <hi>corrupt reaſon,</hi> Revel. 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third, whereby he agrees with <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>heavenly man,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. This laſt we muſt <hi>deny to be ours; not I, but the grace of God which was with me. The fear of God and keeping his Commandment,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all the man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccle. 12. what ever elſe is in the man, it's either the <hi>beaſt</hi> or the <hi>devil:</hi> Both which make up the <hi>corrupt ſelf,</hi> which the <hi>true man muſt deny.</hi> The <hi>Grace of God which is able to ſave all men hath appeared,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>teaching us to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts,</hi> Tit. 2. <hi>Such as fight againſt the ſoul,</hi> they are the <hi>ſenſual and brutiſh ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the ſame <hi>Grace of God</hi> arms the believer with <hi>weapons might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y hrough God, for the caſting down imaginations</hi> or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, <hi>and every high thing that exal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God,</hi> and bringing <hi>into captivity every thought unto the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4, 5. That's the <hi>denyal of the diabolical ſelf.</hi> What ſtore of matter doth this juncture of time afford for <hi>ſelf-denyal!</hi> Such as the Apoſtle feared he ſhould finde among his factious <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſuch we may be ſure is to be found among us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20. <hi>Debates, envyings, wrathes, ſtrifes, backbitings, whiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erings, ſwellings, tumules.</hi> This is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>econd ſtep, which who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oever aſcends, he muſt expect aſſaults from the <hi>beaſt</hi> and the <hi>devil,</hi> which he hath <hi>denyed,</hi> and renounced. And therefore it will be neceſſary, that he aſcend alſo the third.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Croſs; which he muſt take up dayly.</hi> But what is the <hi>Croſs?</hi> Or rather what is it not? He who undertook to write a <hi>Clavis Scripturae, a key wherewith to open the Scripture,</hi> ſaith the Croſs is, <hi>Omnis generis Calamitates, piorum preſertim veritatis cauſa toleratas.</hi> Calamities of every kind of the godly born, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for the truths ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:65679:37"/>
But if affliction, or perſecution, or calamity, ſuch as he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, were the <hi>Croſs,</hi> then muſt we <hi>take them up and bare them,</hi> as we are commanded to <hi>take up the croſs;</hi> But we are warranted to flee perſecutions, Math. 10.23. <hi>when they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you in one City, flee to another;</hi> but verſe 38 of that chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he tells them, that <hi>he who taketh not up his croſs and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, is not worthy of him.</hi> Beſides, its poſſible that the <hi>Christian Church</hi> may for ſome time be without perſecution; For Acts 9.31. <hi>then had the Churches reſt throughout all Judea and Galilee, and Samaria, and were edified, and walking in the fear of God, and comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, were multiplied.</hi> But ſhall we think that the <hi>Christians</hi> then laid aſide the <hi>croſs,</hi> which our Lord commands thoſe who will be <hi>his diſciples, to take up daily and follow him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Adde hereunto, that if afflictions were the <hi>croſs which muſt be taken up,</hi> then ſhould onely poor and miſerable men, who could not avoid afflictions, they ſhould <hi>bear the croſs;</hi> but our Lord enjoyns this duty unto all who will be his <hi>Diſciples, Luke</hi> 9.23.</p>
               <p>Nor do I doubt but the reaſon why men encline rather to this <hi>Gloſs,</hi> that <hi>affliction is the croſs,</hi> becauſe all manner of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and tribulations may be born, and yet ſin may remain and live; which generally men love better than their eſtates, their honors, yea their lives.</p>
               <p>I have written of the <hi>Croſs</hi> more largely, becauſe the <hi>bearing of it</hi> is a duty moſt neceſſary, yet almoſt generally miſtaken. What then is it to bear the <hi>Croſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>bearing of the Croſs is the Chriſtian patience,</hi> Revel. 1.9. It conſiſts in <hi>bearing and ſuffering all aſſaults and temptations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſin, from all ſorts of cauſes inward and outward, without our yielding thereunto.</hi> And becauſe this, of all other <hi>Chriſtian duties,</hi> is moſt contrary to the garb and faſhion of the world, which lies <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in the evilone,</hi> expoſed to the <hi>obedience of his luſts,</hi> and is moſt oppoſed and ſpoken againſt; hence it is that the <hi>bearing of the Croſs,</hi> conſiſts alſo in <hi>ſuffering ignominy, ſhame, reproach, curſing, and evil ſpeaking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that we ſee wherein conſiſts our <hi>conformity unto Christ
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65679:37"/>crucified,</hi> viz. <hi>in bearing all aſſaults and temptations unto ſin, with out yielding our conſent thereunto;</hi> as alſo in <hi>bearing ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, &amp; ignominy</hi> which follows thereupon, <hi>from the evil world.</hi> Of the former, the Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eaks, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt,</hi> c. 5. <hi>They who are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh, with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts.</hi> Of the latter, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. <hi>Let us run with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the race that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>conſider him who endured ſuch contradiction of ſinners, againſt himſelf.</hi> Where we have <hi>Chriſts example,</hi> and <hi>our imitation</hi> of it expreſſed in thoſe words; <hi>Let us run with patience that race which is ſet before us:</hi> and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Jeſus, that he might ſanctifie the people with his own blood, ſuffered without the gate.</hi> There's <hi>Chriſts example; our imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion followes,</hi> verſe 13. <hi>Let us go forth therefore unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach.</hi> When <hi>our old man is now crucified with Chriſt, that the body of ſin is deſtroyed, that henceforth we may not ſerve ſin,</hi> then all the heavenly minded ones, all the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted <hi>Eagles meet at the dead Body;</hi> And <hi>Chriſt being lifted up, will draw all men unto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, and not till then, appears <hi>Equity,</hi> ſo that <hi>whatſoever we would that men ſhould do to us, even ſo we ſhould do to them.</hi> For while our <hi>iniquittes ſeparate between us and our God, while our hands are defiled with blood, and our fingers with iniquity; while our lips ſpeak lies, and our tongue mutters perverſeneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>while our feet run to evil, and make haſte to ſhed innocent blood; while our thoughts are thoughts of iniquity, while waſting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction are in our pathes, we cannot know the way of Peace; nor is there any judgement in our goings: For having made ourſelves crooked pathes, whoſoever goeth therein ſhall not finde peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence followes a <hi>ſpiruual blindneſs of minde, deſperation, guilty conſcience, apoſtaſie, and revolting from God.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>terras Aſtrea reliquit. Judgement is turned away backward, and uſtice ſtandeth a far off, for truth is fallen in the ſtreet,</hi> and trodden under foot, becauſe we depart not from iniquity, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.13. By reaſon of theſe <hi>obſtructions in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> it comes to paſs, that <hi>equity cannot enter,</hi> Eſay 59.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:65679:38"/>
But when as by <hi>Humility, Self-denyal,</hi> and <hi>taking up the Croſs,</hi> theſe impediments are removed, and they <hi>who are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts,</hi> they meet in the way of <hi>righteouſneſs, judgement</hi> and <hi>equity,</hi> Prov. 2.9. Then the <hi>way of Peace</hi> is opened and made known.</p>
               <p>For whereas the <hi>univerſal righteouſneſs</hi> conſiſts in privative and poſitive duties, <hi>departing from evil, and doing good,</hi> as the Prophets advice i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, putting off the old man, and putting on the new, mortifying ſin, and living unto God,</hi> the effect of both, <hi>is Peace; depart from evil and do good, ſeek peace, and perſue it,</hi> Pſalm 34.14. And <hi>the work of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is peace, and the effect of righteouſneſs is quietneſs and aſſurance for ever.</hi> Which is a <hi>demonſtration of peace, quietneſs and aſſurance</hi> from the cauſe of them, which is <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> and, to confirm it to us, as moſt certain, the Prophet repeats the cauſe, <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> Eſay 32.17.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ratio cauſandi,</hi> or <hi>cauſality</hi> will appear from hence, <hi>Peace</hi> is the <hi>compendium</hi> and <hi>abridgement</hi> of all temporal and eternal happineſs. <hi>And righteouſneſs and holyneſs,</hi> which ſometime are taken for the ſame, are the image of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12. as <hi>Plato</hi> with the ſcripture, affirms, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whereby we are enabled to enjoy that happineſs, that <hi>Eye-ſalve</hi> whereby we ſee God; for God cannot be approached unto but by ſomewhat of himſelf. The eye cannot ſee the ſun, but by being informed by the light of the ſun; <hi>In thy light ſhall we ſee light.</hi> Since therefore <hi>righteouſneſs and holyneſs</hi> is of God, it's neceſſary for the obtaining and en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oying the <hi>peace, reſt, quietneſs and aſſurance for ever,</hi> as the Scripture often teſtifies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Righteouſneſs, righteouſneſs ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt live and inherit the Land. Righteouſneſs and peace have kiſſed each other.</hi> Pſal. 85.10. which the Apoſtle figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively underſtood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. Melchiſedec <hi>is firſt by interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion King of righteouſneſs, and after that King of</hi> Salem, <hi>which is King of peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor let it ſeem ſtrange that I ſeem to have gone ſo far about to ſeek the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The things that make for peace,</hi> and meanes to advance it. It is a true, ſolid, and durable <hi>peace,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65679:38"/>which I propounded to my ſelf to enquire after, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the two divided parties. Such a <hi>peace</hi> cannot conſiſt with iniquity. <hi>There is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God.</hi> Yet how many at this day promiſe themſelves <hi>peace</hi> without <hi>the things which make for peace?</hi> Againſt ſuch, the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth moſt heavy judgements, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29 19. Yet do not many reſolve to walk in their old corrupt ways, wherein they walked before, and thereby brought the wrath of God upon themſelves, and the whole land? And yet they hope for <hi>peace,</hi> and cry and call upon God to come unto them in their <hi>evil ways</hi> and <hi>walk with them;</hi> but they will not ſtir out of their own <hi>evil ways</hi> to walk with God in his <hi>way of righteouſneſs and peace.</hi> Yea, and do they not think to be accourted <hi>righteous,</hi> becauſe Chriſt is righteous? But does not our Lord ſay ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely the contrary, <hi>Shall I count them pure with the wicked balances, and the bag of decitful weights?</hi> Mich. 6.</p>
               <p>Yea, many there are who promiſe themſelves <hi>peace,</hi> yet practiſe not <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> which is the immediate, adequate, and propor cauſe of it. It's an heavy complaint, and I am afraid it's too true, that many who profeſs themſelves the <hi>righteous people,</hi> are yet no <hi>juſt dealers,</hi> that they will <hi>lie, cheat, over-reach their brethren in bargaining,</hi> &amp;c. and all under a <hi>form of godlineſs and pretence of righteouſneſs.</hi> They remember not, that <hi>he is righteous who doth righteous things,</hi> 1 John 3.7.</p>
               <p>Beſides, many there are even of thoſe who <hi>profeſs religion,</hi> and know that <hi>the effect of Righteouſneſs is Peace,</hi> who ſingle out ſome certain duties and parts of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and lay on them the ſtreſs of all <hi>religion;</hi> as <hi>keeping the ſabbath,</hi> as one of the <hi>greateſt Commandements,</hi> if not the very <hi>greateſt of all;</hi> which yet the Jewes accounted one of the <hi>leaſt.</hi> When, in regard of many other duties, that was diſpenſed withall, as, in <hi>periculo vitae ceſſat ſabbatum,</hi> when life is in danger, the ſabbath ceaſeth. Nor does our Lord blame them, but juſtifies them who lead their Ox or their Aſs to the water on the <hi>ſabbath day;</hi> their mercy to their beaſt excuſed the breach of the <hi>ſabbath.</hi> Yea, the Prieſts brake the <hi>ſabbath, and were guiltleſs.</hi> Beſides this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>ſabbath,</hi> they urge <hi>abſtinence from curſing and ſwearing,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65679:39"/>and drunkenneſs;</hi> All which, though parts of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> yet, upon the matter they tend rather to make men <hi>good husbands then good Chriſtians.</hi> Mean time other <hi>great things of the Law,</hi> and main parts of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> are forgotten, as <hi>having God for our God, to love him with all our heart, all our ſoul, all our might, and with all our underſtanding, and to love our neighbor as our ſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o fear God and honor the King. To be ſubject to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers and that not onely for fear, but alſo for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake. Not to kill, not to commit adultery, not to ſteal, not to lie, but every one to ſpeak truth to his neighbor, not to bear falſe witneſs, not to go beyond our brother in bargaining, not to covet. To do, udgement, love mercy, and to walk humbly with our God. To deny our ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves, and take up our croſs dayly, and follow the Lord Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. unto which our Lord Jeſus directs us as the more <hi>weighty things of the law, and goſpel,</hi> and wherein the <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whoſe effect is peace,</hi> conſiſts; of theſe <hi>Altum ſilentium,</hi> few or no words of theſe, or, if words, but words. <hi>Chriſt hath done theſe things for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I muſt not omit certain other ſervices, which are of high eſtimation, and indeed of far greater account then thoſe now recited. Such are <hi>days of humiliation and prayer, hearing the word, receiving the Sacrament;</hi> which, for their greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, are called <hi>Gods Ordinances,</hi> which are more venerable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſome, then the <hi>Commandements of God,</hi> which are called his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> Levit. 18.4. and elſewhere, with theſe and ſuch like Temple-worſhips the hypocritical people of old deceived themſelves, which were moſt-what ineffectual, as <hi>Zech.</hi> 7. they kept a <hi>faſt threeſcore and ten</hi> years; the Lord owned it not, as done to himſelf, ſo that a man may perform ſuch ſervice unto God his whole life time (for that's the age of a man, ſaith <hi>David</hi>) yet all that time not pleaſe God, which I much fear, may be ſaid of our like kinde of Worſhips. We had our <hi>monethly faſts</hi> for many years, when we <hi>ſmote with the fiſt of wickedneſs;</hi> at which very time was the inundation of all unrighte ouſneſs, and all abomination in the land, <hi>and blood touched blood,</hi> and the hand of God, was ſtretched out againſt us. The Lord inſtructed <hi>Solomon,</hi> how to award national judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65679:39"/>and upon what terms, he will give <hi>peace</hi> to the land. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.4. <hi>If my people who are called by my name, do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, and pray and ſeek my face, and turn from their evil ways, then will I hear from heaven, and forgive their ſin, and heal the land.</hi> Many of us ſeem to exerciſe the three former, <hi>humble themſelves,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>ſeek Gods face,</hi> and glory much that they are a <hi>praying people.</hi> And if the Lord vouchſafe any good ſucceſs to them, preſently they aſcribe it unto their prayers, as the effect of them. Mean time little care is taken of <hi>turning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> their evil ways,</hi> little exhortation thereunto, whereas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed therein lies the principal ſtreſs of the Lords direction. And commonly men have three reaſons eſpecially why the <hi>turning from their evil ways,</hi> is not ſo much urged. 1. They think it impoſſible wholly ſo to do. Yea, 2. herein they are the more remiſs, leſt they ſhould fall into that new hereſie (found out by <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcator,</hi> as I take it) of the <hi>Perfectiſts.</hi> And 3. leſt they ſhould ſeem to merit by ſo doing. And for theſe reaſons ſome, I fear, conſcientiouſly abſtain from doing good.</p>
               <p>But unleſs there be an <hi>univerſal turning from all and every one of our evil ways,</hi> all our <hi>humbling,</hi> all our <hi>praying,</hi> all our <hi>pretence of ſeeking Gods face,</hi> will be utterly in vain and to no purpoſe, although the beſt men on earth ſhould pray for us. When the people had deſired <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for them, he promiſed ſo to do, but unleſs they <hi>turned from their evil ways,</hi> he aſſures them, his <hi>prayer</hi> would be ineffectual; as indeed afterward it proved, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that notwithſtanding all the <hi>pageantry,</hi> all the <hi>oſtentation of Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gion,</hi> all the <hi>partial</hi> and <hi>falſe righteouſneſs,</hi> the envy, the pride, the covereouſneſs, the wrath, the gluttony, the chambering and wantonneſs, the ſlothfulneſs in all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duties, generally the ſin remains, and conſequently no <hi>peace</hi> can be hoped for, which is the <hi>proper effect of righteouſneſs.</hi> For <hi>what peace,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jehu, ſo long as the whoredoms of</hi> Jezebel <hi>and her witchcrafts are ſo many?</hi> There is an inconſiſtency, and incompoſſibility of <hi>peace</hi> with the <hi>whoredoms and witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts of</hi> Jezebel. <hi>Jezebel</hi> hath a diverſe <hi>Etymon,</hi> either <hi>Inſula
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65679:40"/>habitaculi,</hi> an Iſland of habitation and dwelling, as the <hi>Iſland</hi> wherein we dwell; or <hi>Inſula ſterquilinii,</hi> an <hi>Iſland</hi> of a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill. And this latter, the Scripture it ſelf warrants, 2 <hi>King</hi> 9.38. The <hi>carcaſe of</hi> Jezebel <hi>ſhall be like dung</hi> upon the face of the field. So <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.22. O how unhappily is this <hi>Etymon</hi> this Notation fulfilled in this <hi>Iſland! Jezebel</hi> ſpiritually under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. and her <hi>whoredoms</hi> and <hi>witcherafts. Whoredom</hi> is ſpiritually <hi>idolatry,</hi> a moſt known metaphor. <hi>Diſobedience is</hi> underſtood by <hi>witcheraft,</hi> Gal. 3.1. By theſe and all <hi>open ſin,</hi> and <hi>falſe righteouſneſs,</hi> this <hi>Iſland</hi> (which, the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>man told King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, was Gods kingdom by theſe, this <hi>Iſland</hi> is made a <hi>dunghil,</hi> &amp; therefore what <hi>peace</hi> can be unto it?</p>
               <p>Since therefore, <hi>my beloved Brethren, of both perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> ſuch abundance of <hi>iniquity</hi> and <hi>falſe righteouſneſs</hi> ſuch as the Apoſtle calls <hi>dung, Phil.</hi> 3. hath over-ſpread this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> in it, and hidden the <hi>way of peace</hi> from us; and ſince the <hi>partial falſe righteouſneſs</hi> hath proved uſeleſs, and ineffectual for the diſcovery and finding out that <hi>way,</hi> let us all and every one of us, <hi>proſe quiſque,</hi> enquire and <hi>ſeek for peace</hi> and <hi>perſue it</hi> in thoſe narrow and untrodden <hi>pathes,</hi> and follow the example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath gone the ſame <hi>way</hi> before us, <hi>that we ſhould follow his ſteps;</hi> And <hi>let the ſame mind be in us,</hi> and every one of us, <hi>which was alſo in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto the death, even the death of the Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us ſeek <hi>peace</hi> in theſe <hi>ways</hi> infallibly and unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly leading thereunto. Let us <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>perſue peace</hi> as eagerly as a man would <hi>perſue his enemy,</hi> and follow hard after it; yet let us not uſe it as an <hi>enemy,</hi> but as a <hi>dear friend,</hi> and ſuch as we would make an <hi>umpire</hi> of our differences: and ſo let every one of us entertain <hi>peace</hi> in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> perſwades, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let the <hi>Peace of God ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrate and rule in your hearts,</hi> Col. 3.15. as when we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, commonly mutinous and ſeditious thoughts ariſe in our hearts, whereof ſome ſtir us up to <hi>revenge; ſuffer this, and ſuffer all,</hi> &amp;c. but others coming moſt what after the former, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſecundae cogitationes ſapientiores,</hi>) theſe ſecond
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65679:40"/>
                  <hi>thoughts</hi> perſwade us to <hi>humility, ſelf-denyal, taking up the croſs, long-ſuffering, rendring good for evil, and overcoming evil with goodneſs,</hi> &amp;c. what's therefore now to be done? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Let the peace of God rule in your hearts, and that will guide our thoughts, wills, and affections into the way of peace:</hi> Let that <hi>peace of God umpire our differences.</hi> Let that <hi>peace moderate, arbitrate, and rule in our hearts, whereunto we are called in one body.</hi> Will one member contend with, or do injury to another? O no; but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member is compaſſionate and helpful, and bears the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſs of another. The holy Apoſtle labours for this <hi>peace</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>the Church,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Allegory</hi> of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers mutu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erviceableneſs one to other, and to the <hi>body the Church,</hi> that there ſhould be no <hi>ſchiſm</hi> in the <hi>body,</hi> but that the members ſhould have the ſame care one of another, and whether one member ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it; or <hi>one member be honored, all the members rejoyce with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe laſt words contain an hard leſſon in them. For it is much to be feared, that our <hi>envy</hi> at our fellow members <hi>honors,</hi> and our <hi>ambitious</hi> deſires of them for ourſelves, hath made this <hi>ſchiſm</hi> and <hi>preach of peace</hi> in the <hi>body;</hi> which the Apoſtle endeavours to prevent, when he tells us, <hi>Ye are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular.</hi> And how unſeemly is the <hi>tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> or ſwelling of <hi>ambition,</hi> or the <hi>Maraſmus</hi> or Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>envy in the body of Chriſt?</hi> Eſpecially ſince the <hi>honors</hi> of Chriſts members ariſe with their proficiencies, as was ſhewen before; and their variety is ordered of God: And therefore the Apoſtle adds; that <hi>God hath ſet</hi> ſome in the <hi>Church, firſt</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>ſecondly</hi> Prophets, <hi>thirdly</hi> Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> implying forcibly, that if men duely conſidered that this ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of divine <hi>honors,</hi> is by <hi>divine inſtitution,</hi> the evil ſpirits of <hi>ambition and envy</hi> would ſoon be laid, eſpecially in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſts body:</hi> And therefore the ſame Apoſtle exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to this <hi>unity,</hi> he begins at the loweſt ſtep of <hi>Jac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bs</hi> ladder, <hi>Humility;</hi> walk with <hi>all lowlineſs and meekneſs, wtth long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love; endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace. There is one body and one ſpirit, even as you are called in one hope of our calling, one
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65679:41"/>Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, and through all, and in you all. But unto every one of us is given grace, according to the meaſure <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of the gift Chriſt.</hi> And leſt this different meaſure of grace might raiſe the evil ſpirits of <hi>ambition</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> he calls thoſe digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons, Gods <hi>gifts unto men</hi> which he gave, ſome <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſome <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. which <hi>gifts</hi> he <hi>gives</hi> for the <hi>perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, until we all come into the unity of the faith and knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my brethren! let this umprage, and <hi>arbitation</hi> of peace be wrought <hi>firſt</hi> in every one of our ſouls; For until this <hi>peace</hi> be promoted <hi>at home</hi> in every mans own <hi>heart,</hi> eſpecially in every one of yours, my brethren, who are of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> how can it be hoped, that you ſhould advance it <hi>abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad</hi> among the people? <hi>Nihil dat quod non habet.</hi> How can you impart to them the <hi>ſpiritual gift of peace,</hi> if you have it not <hi>your ſelves?</hi> Yea, how can it be but that you muſt <hi>embitter</hi> them with the <hi>ſpirit of contention,</hi> while your ſelves are acted by the ſame <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The people have a kind of <hi>natural equity</hi> among them, and, eſpecially fince the long civil Wars in the Nation, and are of themſelves diſpoſed to peace. And who are they who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſe them, and diſqulet them but the <hi>Miniſters?</hi> As the long Wars in <hi>Germany</hi> (to come no nearer home) too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently have proved. St. <hi>John</hi> Revelation 17.15. tells us, that the people are Waters: And the reſemblance between them may eſpecially be this: The Sea of it ſelf, though it be the greateſt <hi>gathering together of many waters,</hi> yet would it be <hi>quiet and calm as</hi> a river, did not the <hi>winds</hi> raiſe the waves, and make it rage, <hi>and caſt up mire and dirt.</hi> And who raiſed the waves of the waters [the populacy] in all theſe Wars in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> but the <hi>evil ſpirits</hi> acting the <hi>Miniſters?</hi> And what miſchief will not they do, if they meet together? <hi>If Lovi</hi> and <hi>Than,</hi> the <hi>prieſt</hi> and the <hi>dragon</hi> be joyned together, they make <hi>Leviathan,</hi> little leſs then the devil incarnate; becauſe <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65679:41"/>optimi eſt peſſima,</hi> the corruption of the beſt is the worſt of all. Therefore St. <hi>John, Revel.</hi> 16.13. ſaw <hi>three unclean ſpirits like frogs come out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe Prophet;</hi> which he interprets the <hi>ſpirits of devils</hi> working miracles, which <hi>go forth unto the Kings of the earth, and of the whole world, to gather them together to the battel of the great day of God Almighty.</hi> O what an hideous degeneration is this, that the <hi>Ambaſſadors of peace</hi> ſhould become the <hi>heraulds of war!</hi> But <hi>Cynthius aurem vellit,</hi> and bids m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Reſpice titulum.</hi> I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my <hi>time,</hi> and not too much weary my <hi>Reader,</hi> and remember him of my <hi>method.</hi> I am engaged in the enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expedients and means how to compoſe the differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two divided parties. I have hitherto mentioned thoſe neceſſary inward means without which the ſolid <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>reconciliation</hi> will never be obtained. For what ever means may be uſed without theſe, they will onely <hi>skin over</hi> the <hi>feſtered ſore,</hi> which will <hi>break out</hi> again. It is onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>healing Doctrine</hi> which will cure all putrified ulcers, and diſtempers of the ſoul. This had not been made uſe of when the Lord complained, that the Prophets had <hi>healed</hi> the <hi>hreach</hi> of the daughter of his people ſleightly, ſaying, <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> when there was <hi>no peace,</hi> Jer. 6.14. we ſhall therefore in good order, after the uſe of inward means, call in the help of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>And firſt it will be an hard task, to perſwade the people to forbear the <hi>choice of the Miniſter.</hi> They have nor precept nor example for it, in holy Scripture, nor practiſe of the ancient Church to countenance it; But ſuch a peſtilent cuſtom hath crept in among us of late, by the activity of ſome fiery zealots, that thereby they might engage the <hi>Miniſters</hi> to compliance with the Government of ſome <hi>forein Church,</hi> and <hi>undermine their own;</hi> that they might <hi>teach the Miniſter</hi> what he ſhould teach them; that they might <hi>fore-ſeaſon</hi> him, who ſhould be their <hi>ſalt,</hi> and as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to make their rule crooked, becauſe they themſelves are ſo.</hi> That hereby they might diſaffect him to the <hi>Doctrine
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65679:42"/>and Rites of the Church,</hi> and foment a party againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it. And for this end they have <hi>created a new officer</hi> in the Church, who muſt be levened with the ſame ſowre <hi>leven of the Phariſees.</hi> This <hi>Office</hi> they have made out of the name of <hi>Lector,</hi> who was onely a publick <hi>Reader</hi> of Scripture, and no <hi>preacher</hi> in the ancient Church. And great care is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that he be the peoples <hi>creature,</hi> as <hi>his Office is,</hi> that he may unteach in the afternoon what the Parſon delivers in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and, if poſſible, work him out; from this corrupt <hi>fountain</hi> have iſſued thoſe many <hi>ſtreames of blood</hi> in the three Nations. So great miſchiefs have proceeded from the peoples <hi>choice of their Miniſter;</hi> for which they have no warrant in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as hath been ſaid, except that which I hope they will not follow, and ſo it will be null to them, the example of the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> who choſe <hi>Micha's</hi> idolatrous <hi>chaplain for their Prieſt.</hi> Add hereunto, that as the people have no right, ſo neither have they skill to make <hi>choice of the Miniſter,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, every man judges well of what he knowes, were it not much more ſafe to commit that choice to the Fathers of the Church <hi>who watch for the peoples ſouls, and muſt give an account?</hi> Heb. 13.17.</p>
               <p>But as hard a thing it will be to diſſwade the <hi>Miniſter</hi> from ſubmitting to the <hi>peoples choice.</hi> Yet all ingenuous men will conſider, what hath been ſaid, and what ungodlineſs it is to mancipate the truth of God to the judgement of ignorant men, and how unhanſom it is to be <hi>taken by the mouth,</hi> and lead like an <hi>horſe</hi> or an <hi>aſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, the people moſt what love none but their own <hi>creatures,</hi> and look upon others as <hi>enemies,</hi> and heartily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their ruine, as proof hath been made by thouſands of examples in theſe late deplorable times. Whence ariſeth a caſe which extreamly diſturbs the <hi>peace of the Church,</hi> and that unavoidably, while men follow the ſuggeſtions of fleſh and blood, &amp; uſe not the means before mentioned: the party <hi>eſecting the Miniſter</hi> commonly retaines the old <hi>hatred.</hi> (That kind of people like the God whom they imagine to themſelves, <hi>hate</hi> and <hi>love</hi> whom ever they <hi>hate and love</hi> unchangeably and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually.)
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65679:42"/>The <hi>Miniſter ejected</hi> retaines alſo <hi>his deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</hi> When therefore reſtitution is made, as in the <hi>Jubile,</hi> and every one returns to his own poſſeſſion, what an irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable jarring muſt there needs be? It's a common complaint all the Nation over. What hope can there be that the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in this caſe, ſhould <hi>edifie</hi> the people?</p>
               <p>When the <hi>old hatred</hi> remains on <hi>the one part, and deſire of revenge on the other,</hi> what <hi>peace</hi> can be made? How ſhall the people be <hi>edified?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall propound an <hi>Expedient;</hi> But as when the Poets had entangled themſelves in their plots ſo that they could by no means extricate themſelves, they brought down their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a God to diſentangle them;</hi> there is no other way to <hi>unravel</hi> this otherwiſe inextricable entanglement, but by imploring the Soveraign power who alone can make this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient effectual. What if <hi>an exchange of Livings</hi> were made? by that means the diſſenting parties would be at greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from other; and as affections and all other <hi>facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoul work powerfully in the preſence of their object;</hi> So on the contrary, it might be hoped, that the <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>deſire of revenge</hi> would by <hi>abſence</hi> and <hi>diſtance</hi> be more remiſs, and at length vaniſh. If this means be not ſufficient, or not poſſible, or fecible to remove this Offence out of the <hi>way of peace</hi> (as indeed none outward can be without thoſe inward before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,) I ſhall leave it to others of better judgement as a problem, and call in to our help the <hi>Patrons of livings</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their <hi>Clarks</hi> to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be ſent as <hi>Miniſters unto the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nimirum vitio vertitur iis qui jus patronatus habent, quod fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias ſuas docent Eccleſiae patrimonio; quod beneficia conferant ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica in clericos ſuos ſub conditione non-decimandi, quod vol praeſenti mercede, vel certa lucri ſpe, vel favore indebito, vel ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quaepiam cauſa (ſiquidem plurima ſunt myſteria iniquitatis) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> inducti, non Dei-metuentes &amp; vere Presbyteres, at ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines male moratos, neophytos, juvenes imperitos rerum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tina prophetarum ſchola non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> manſerunt uſque dum barbae creverint, non Theologos, at Grammaticos, Rhetoras,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65679:43"/>ant <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Philoſophia <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> modica ſcientia non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte inflatos Epiſcope praeſent averint ordinandes; quos audire ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſolos neque alios alibi, vi conſtitutenium Eccleſiaſticarum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe habent parochiani.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt alſo implore the aid and aſſiſtance of both the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, with thoſe of the Neighbo Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neque ferant aegre venerabiles in utraque Academia, Praefecti ſociiſque Collegiorum ſi memorem quod paſſim queraentur homines, Ariſtotelem &amp; Philoſophos apud vos legi, negligi Moſem &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetas. Adoleſcentes in utr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mque partem diſputandi ſcientiam calluiſſe, at recte vivendi artem non didiciſſe. Ignaros parumque proficientes coſdemque nequam homines ac nebulones non gradibus tantum tituliſque literaturae humanioris oruari, verum etiam teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio virtutis, pietatis &amp; gratiae deceramento coheneſtari. Praeter etiam quam quod hoc planiſſime mendacium ſit in perpetuam rei memoriam duraturum, imponit ita inſuper ejuſmodi falſum Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium Reverendiſſimis Eccleſiae Patribus Epiſcopis, uti virtute illius (aut vitio potius) hi nefaris homines Presbyteri ordinentur; animaeque populorum larvatis iſtis hypocritis concreditae magis &amp; magis, uts Beatus Gregorius ait, aediſicentur in Gehennam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Siquidem hujuſmodi homunciones ex Academia non-tanquam perſonae ſingulares exeunt &amp; ſoli ſibi ſolis improbi, at Radices omnes Communitatis (ut Aquinas ait) vel Judices; vel Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati, vel Procuratores, vel cujus illi cumque nominis in utroque foro Legulaei; vel Irenarchae in Republica, vel Eccleſiae Miniſtri, vel Curatores, Ludive Magiſtri ut plurimum evadunt, unaque ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ab Academia nequitiam literis, gradibus ac titvlis arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam in regnum devehunt univerſum. Haec ego ſaepius opprobriae in utramque Academiam à Sectariis &amp; factioſis hominibus cum gemitu audivi; atque utinam haec omnia eſſent per quam falſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fima!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeterum in magnam ſpem veni, ex anno jam redeunte Jubilae, antiquam, cum venerandis Praefectis, redituram diſciplinam, moreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Academia, into etiam Deo dignos; quo fiet uti qua apud vos enutritia primitus atque educata partium diſſidia, prudentia ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra &amp; authoritate ſopiantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But above all others we muſt call the School-maſter to our
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65679:43"/>help, who if ſuch as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ught to be, he is the moſt ſerviceable inſtrument of all men of faculties in the Nation, to promote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his work; though it be moſt true even of him who is <hi>Optimus Maximus,</hi> the moſt great and good God, <hi>and of all good men, and good things, Optima &amp; maxima minimi aſtimantur,</hi> the beſt and greateſt are leaſt eſteemed. Happy man who hath his lot among theſe! as no doubt the good School-maſter hath, who, above all other, <hi>ſerves God and man</hi> in this affair. And well he may, for he hath abſolute power: as the Tyrant <hi>Dionyſius</hi> being elected out of his Kingdom, choſe to be a <hi>School maſter,</hi> ſaying <hi>Regnabo tamen,</hi> yet I will reign. 2. He hath the moſt capable ſubject to work upon, <hi>Udum &amp; molle lutum,</hi> matter ſoft and pliable to his hand. His work will proſper, if he be ſo happy as to receive it out of a good hand, from parents who fear GOD, honor the KING, and are diſcreet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and be further ſo ſucceſsful as to deliver his work into a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand, which may finiſh it, a father-like Tutor in the Univerſity. Theſe two <hi>men of faculties</hi> if encouraged, may render this Church and Nation, the beſt and happyeſt in the world. But I deſpair of finding many ſuch men or favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them: though ſome few I know (I cannot but think ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably of <hi>Weſtminſter-ſchool,</hi>) and his Majeſty gives counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to all learned and pious men.</p>
               <p>But neither God nor men will help us, unleſs we help our ſelves. I ſhall therefore commend to both parties the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their <hi>former</hi> and preſent eſtate; and deal with them firſt a-part, then jointly. And firſt conſider ye my Brethren of <hi>the Presbytery;</hi> Are not ye the men who many years ſince complained and groaned under the <hi>tyrannical imperiouſneſs and domineering of the Biſhops (know your own words.)</hi> And ought not yee being then delivered from that yoke, to have dealt favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with your oppreſſors, ſince yee knew the heart of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed (it's the Lords argument to his people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.9.) ought yee not to have returned good for evil? Should you not have endeavoured to overcome evil with goodneſs? I ſay not how <hi>non-Chriſtianè</hi> (to ſay no more,) yee ruled over them. And ſince the Lord hath returned their captivity, and inclined
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65679:44"/>the Kings heart to make you ſharer with them in their dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and honors, and afforded you greater indulgence then ever any of your party ever had in this Church, ought you not to ſtudy to be quiet and do your own buſineſs, and leave the Government of the Church and Kingdom to thoſe to whom it belongs?</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo adviſedly what Overtures yee have had, and what opportunities have been put into your hand, of rayſing that Government which yee ſo much long for; Have yee not cut your way toward it, with the ſword? Hath it not been eſtabliſhed by civil ſanctions? Yet you cannot but ſee that, by reaſon of your ambition of <hi>more power, and ſtill more power,</hi> and of being eſtabliſhed <hi>jure divino,</hi> how <hi>the hand of God hath been ſo</hi> ſignally againſt you all along, that yee could never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe that <hi>power</hi> you had, except only ſo far and ſo ſhort a time as to render it odious, and to make the Nation weary of it. Ought you not, my brethren, from theſe conſiderations, herein to acquieſe and reſt in Gods determination? Or, ſince <hi>all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of God,</hi> which, by his many providential acts, appears that he denies to you, will yee weary your ſelves, contend with your brethren, and weary them, be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, weary our God alſo,</hi> and all in vain?</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo you my brethren of <hi>Epiſcopal perſwaſion;</hi> and remember the time of <hi>your great tribulation,</hi> whereinto yee were brought, not without your own ſins, by what hand ſoever you were brought into it. Acknowledge that God is juſt, and own his good hand in bringing you <hi>out of that great tribulation. Leave vengeance to him to whom it belongeth. Put on Charity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, which is the bond of perfectneſs, and let the peace of God umpire</hi> all differences <hi>in your hearts, to which alſo you are called in one body;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>And be ye thankful</hi> (that's a good ſenſe: but it's a better, and more fit for that place,) <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſi eſtote</hi> (according to <hi>Hierom</hi>) be <hi>ye gracious, amiable, and lovely,</hi> according to that proverbial precept, which it were to be wiſhed that we all obeyed, —<hi>Ut ameris amabilis eſto,</hi> that thou mayeſt be beloved, be lovely. Shew this love and <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God</hi> to your brethren of the Presbytery. You know the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:65679:44"/>
                  <hi>heart of oppreſſed men,</hi> (it's Gods argument to his people, why they ſhould love the Egyptians) and it is the <hi>kindneſs of God</hi> to overcome evil with goodneſs, and to love our enemies.</p>
               <p>Let theſe conſiderations prevail with you above your <hi>ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> above your <hi>revenge.</hi> For conſider adviſedly and in the ſight of God, and deal truely with your own heart; what moves thee to deſire a <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> a <hi>Deanary,</hi> a <hi>Prebend?</hi> the <hi>Biſhops, Deans and Chapters lands,</hi> or <hi>the land of the living?</hi> The <hi>Honor</hi> annexed to that high place <hi>Digi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> monſtrari ac di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cier, hic eſt;</hi> to be called <hi>Rabbi, Rabbi;</hi> Or that higheſt <hi>Honor that cometh of God onely;</hi> whether the eaſe hoped for, or the good work? Whether thou rather deſire the <hi>Corps</hi> and <hi>body of a Prebend,</hi> or rather the <hi>duty</hi> of it, <hi>Hoſpitality, Almeſgiving,</hi> the <hi>trayning up of novices and yong men,</hi> and <hi>fitting them for the work of the Lord,</hi> that they may grow up and become <hi>Presbyters, Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Elders;</hi> all which is the <hi>ſoul and ſpirit of theſe dignities,</hi> and I doubt not but it was the <hi>end at which the Founders and Donors aimed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if thou attain to theſe <hi>Honors,</hi> conſider, the <hi>the greateſt is ſervant of all.</hi> That the <hi>Biſhaps</hi> are <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Shepherds;</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Office</hi> as inferres and requires ſutable acts to the <hi>relations;</hi> as that the <hi>Fathers deal fatherly with their children,</hi> though they too often <hi>ſtubborn children;</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> did <hi>Num.</hi> 11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. that they <hi>rule the flock pedo non gladio,</hi> rather with the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> then with the <hi>rod;</hi> rather with the <hi>rod</hi> then with the <hi>ſword.</hi> That they are <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that is, <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the Church, and like the Lord the great <hi>Biſhop of our ſouls,</hi> they <hi>overſee many things, and wink at ſmall faults,</hi> as the Lord doth <hi>Acts</hi> 17. That, as they <hi>overſee</hi> all, ſo all <hi>ſee</hi> them; and ſuch as they <hi>ſee</hi> their <hi>overſeers,</hi> ſuch they think it's lawful for them to be; therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> would, that they ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 5. paterns to the flock; And if they ſee them <hi>ſpotted,</hi> they will bring forth a <hi>ſpotted iſſue of evil work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore as the Lord commanded <hi>Micha,</hi> chap. 6.1, 2. ſo let me the meaneſt of you in both your and mine own eſteem, (that's <hi>Micha</hi>) ſpeak unto theſe <hi>Mountaines,</hi> the two ſwollen parties, who, as they ſay of <hi>Mountaines,</hi> cannot meet nor touch
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65679:45"/>one another, but <hi>in puncto:</hi> Yee are too high, too lofty. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the <hi>day of the Lord of hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low,</hi> Eſay 2.12. which muſt come to paſs before we can <hi>ſee the ſalvation of God,</hi> Luke 3.5, 6. The Soveraign Majeſty, the King <hi>who is ſupream,</hi> he hath exceedingly <hi>conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended</hi> and <hi>ſtoopt</hi> to the moderation of your <hi>differences, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned many inſolences, even before pardon was deſired. Declared and reſolved to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mote the power of Godlineſs, and to encourage the exerciſes of Religion publick and private,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>granted and confirmed a liberty to tender conſciences, and that no man ſhall be diſquieted, or called in queſtion for difference of opinions in matter of Religion, which doth not diſturb the peace of the Kingdom.</hi> All which, according to the divine wiſdom and goodneſs in him, he hath manifeſted in that beyond all precedents of former favours, his <hi>moſt prudent and moderate Declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical affaires.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall his Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty, my brethren, make <hi>your Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity, your mutual Love</hi> and <hi>Reconcilation his ſtudy,</hi> and ſhould not <hi>you</hi> much more ſtudy the things which make for <hi>your own peace and unity,</hi> and the <hi>peace of the Church</hi> and <hi>kingdom?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know well, there are many very learned men, and great Students among you of both perſwaſions. And I acknowledge my ſelf much inferiour to many of you; Yet, ſince <hi>Micah</hi> muſt ſpeak to the Mountains, let me be bold to tell you, that there is one main point of learning, wherein many of you have declared your non-proficiency; many of you have not ſtudied to be quiet, and to do your own buſmeſs; which was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>learned</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.11. I know well, that many of you who cannot endure <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, buſie Biſhops in other mens dioceſes; and intermedled with the temporal affaires of the City and Nation, under what pretence? <hi>viz. in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſpiritual things, which is the ſame whereof your ſelves accuſe the <hi>Biſhop of Rome.</hi> Yea, there have not been wanting non-proficients in this ſtudy, on both ſides, who have vigorouſly diſquieted and diſturbed the Church and Kingdom, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65679:45"/>were the moſt notable troublers of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Some of theſe, to humour the people, would tell them what the Kings Office and duty was toward his people, and to prove it out of the Common-prayer-book, <hi>viz.</hi> to preſerve the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge, in wealth, peace, and Godlineſs. And would remember the people what their liberties and properties were, which the King ought to preſerve and maintain. And by this craft they had their wealth, as <hi>Demetrius</hi> told his fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradeſmen; and many a good morſel they got by it; for they had read and were perfect in that rule — <hi>cave ne majorum tibi forte Limina frigeſcant,</hi> that otherwiſe they ſhould have cold entertainment at the great mens tables.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, the King was taught, what his prerogative was, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd what the <hi>peoples duty</hi> was to him; To <hi>give unto</hi> Caeſar the things that are <hi>Caeſars:</hi> that every ſoul ſhould be ſubject to the higher powers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mean time the <hi>King</hi> was not told, what his <hi>duty</hi> was toward his people; Nor the <hi>people</hi> what their <hi>duty</hi> was toward their <hi>King.</hi> So that both heard what the others <hi>duty</hi> was, not what their own was; and hence both parties were embittered one againſt the other, by the <hi>evil ſpirit in the mouth of the Prophets.</hi> Did theſe men do their <hi>own buſineſs?</hi> Surely no. For though they <hi>preached the word,</hi> yet were they <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>abſurd men, and illogical,</hi> they did it <hi>out of due place, unlearned men</hi> who had not <hi>ſtudied to be quiet, and do their own buſineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let it be your <hi>ambition,</hi> my brethren, as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ambitiouſly to ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> and do <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>things proper to your own calling.</hi> Provoke not one another to wrath: But if you be of a wrathful diſpoſition, <hi>turn your wrath upon your ſelves; Be angry and ſin not, be angry with your froward heart that you may not ſin. Envy not one another;</hi> or becauſe there is an <hi>Emulation</hi> in us that would be ſatisfied, ſet it upon the <hi>right object,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>emulate the very beſt gifts, but moſt of all that moſt excellent way of charity.</hi> And if you muſt needs be <hi>provoking one another, let us provoke one another to love and good works,</hi> Hebr. 10.24. <hi>Let all bitterneſs and wrath, and anger, and clamer, and evil ſpeaking,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65679:46"/>be put away from you, with all malice: and be yee kind one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, tender hearted forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you.</hi> And <hi>put on <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, holy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, bowells of mercies, goodneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do yee:</hi> And all this is to be done, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the elect of God; <hi>A quatenus ad omne,</hi> all the elect of God are ſuch.</p>
               <p>That wherein all the <hi>Churches</hi> moſt differ, is the <hi>ſervice of God,</hi> by abuſe of which, the Jewes <hi>pleaſed not God, and were contrary to all men.</hi> 1. Theſſ. 2. Wherefore my brethren, <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal,</hi> glory not in your <hi>ſervice,</hi> but endeavour to <hi>live that life which it points unto.</hi> Nor deſpiſe you your brethren, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are my brethren of Presbyterian perſwaſion, in regard of their <hi>ſervice of God,</hi> as <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> but look well into your own, whether much of it be not a <hi>will-worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord perſwade both your hearts into ſuch <hi>a ſervice of God,</hi> that therein yee may <hi>pleaſe God and Men!</hi> And what <hi>ſervice</hi> is that, but <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> whoſe effect is <hi>peace,</hi> and the work of both, <hi>Joy in the holy Ghoſt? Joy unſpeakable,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>glorified Joy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. and that your <hi>Joy</hi> will be the <hi>Joy of us all.</hi> He who in theſe <hi>is ſerving Chriſt, is acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and approved of men.</hi> And this is the <hi>Kingdome of God,</hi> Rom. 14.17, 18. for the coming of which, we dayly pray. <hi>Now whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any vertue, if there be any pruiſe, think on theſe things, and do them, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finally, my brethren, farewel; Be perfect; be of good comfort; be of one minde; live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you. The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the communion of the holy ghoſt be with you all. Amen!</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:65679:46"/>
            <head>The Reader may be pleaſed to correct theſe more groſs faults eſcaped in Printing.</head>
            <p>PAge 15. line 17. Milevitanus. l. 20. Corinthios. p. 16. l. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ibid. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ibid. l. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. l. 23. are. l. 24. is. l. 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 17. l. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. l. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 19. l. 2. at. p. 29. l. 35. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 30. l. 36. righteouſneſſes. p. 35. l. 6. abuſe. p. 36. l. 26. juſtitia. l. 27. fulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum? l. 29. Epiſcopatus. l. 36. hebdomatim. p. 37. l. 6. nihili. l. 27. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpellicium. l. 30. liturgiam. l. 34 eximant. p. 43, l. 3. inclinations. p. 46. l. 15. propior. p. 48. l. 3. who is King of kings. p. 55. l. 3. paucis. li. 7. bajulo. p. 56. l. 27. whoſe. p. 59. l. 23. abrenuntiation. l. 24 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> l. 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 63. l. 37. born, eſpecially. p. 64. l. 2. bear. p. 69. l. 2. 2 Chorn. 7.14. p. 70. l. 6. <hi>Jezebel</hi> is. p. 93. l. 35. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ibid. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 95. l. 19. objects. l. 32. docent. p. 96. l. 3. conſtitutionum, ibid. neceſſe. l. 33. fiet. p. 98. l. 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 99. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
